<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Autarchy, or, The art of self-government in a moral essay : in three parts : first written to a gentleman in the university, and since fitted for publick use.</title>
            <author>G. B. (George Burghope)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 200 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 90 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69655</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5730</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4200</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12787667</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12787667</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93911</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69655)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93911)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 708:15 or 1277:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Autarchy, or, The art of self-government in a moral essay : in three parts : first written to a gentleman in the university, and since fitted for publick use.</title>
                  <author>G. B. (George Burghope)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[19], 158, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Dorman Newman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The epistle dedicatory" signed: G.B.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Burghope by NUC pre-1956 imprints.  Wing attributes this work to both Burghope (Wing B5730) and George Bright (Wing 4670).</note>
                  <note>This item appears at reels 708:15 and 1277:17.</note>
                  <note>Wing number B4670 cancelled in Wing (CD-ROM).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in Huntington Library and Trinity College Library, Cambridge University.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian ethics.</term>
               <term>Self-control.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:93911:1"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Feb. 6. 1690/1.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Z Iſham,</hi> R. P. D. <hi>Hen.</hi>
               </signed> Epiſc. <hi>Lond.</hi> à ſacris.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93911:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TARCHY:</hi> OR, THE ART OF Self-Government, IN A MORAL ESSAY.</p>
            <p>In Three PARTS.</p>
            <p>Firſt Written to a Gentleman in the Univerſity, and ſince fitted for Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Uſe.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <bibl>Epict.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Dorman Newman,</hi> at the <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Arms</hi> in the <hi>Poultry,</hi> 1691.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:93911:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93911:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable JOHN EARL of <hi>Bridgwater,</hi> Viſcount <hi>Brackly,</hi> and Baron of <hi>Elteſmere,</hi> Lord Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant of the County of <hi>Bucks,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Honoured Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AFter ſo many Years Labours in explaining and inculcating the <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> I doubt the true Notion of it is ſtill unknown (I am ſure the Power of it is) to the common ſort
<pb facs="tcp:93911:3"/> of Chriſtians: Some confine it to this Party, and others to that; and many place it in a Theory of Doctrines never reduc'd into practice, unleſs it be in ſtarcht Hypocriſie, in affected Tones, extemporary Effuſions, enthuſiaſtick In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirations, loud Prayers, and long Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; and the running after ſuch Men, and having their Perſons in Admiration, is that which theſe Men take to be Religion. And moſt make ſuch a noiſe about Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which is the Means, that they have no regard to that which is the End. Mean while there is one thing agreed to by all, of what Sect or Faction ſoever, as neceſſary, though moſt of all neglected, and that is <hi>Morality.</hi> And though this Word is vulgarly taken to ſignifie nothing but a kind of <hi>Heathen Honeſty;</hi> yet I ſhall not fear to ſay, That it is the Eſſential Part of that which we call Religion, and the End of all our Writings and Diſputes
<pb facs="tcp:93911:3"/> about it. For the Chriſtian acceptation of the Word <hi>Morality</hi> is nothing elſe, but the Conformity of our Manners to the Rules of Jeſus, and living as Chriſtians are taught to do by the Principles of their Religion. And this reſpects a Threefold Object, God, our Neighbour, and our Selves. To God we owe Devotion, and the higheſt Fear, Love, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To Man an univerſal Love and Charity: and to our Selves Temperance and Sobriety. And this was the Summ of Practical Religion in the Old Teſtament (as appears by <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cah 6. 8.)</hi> and in the New, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> will inform us, <hi>Tit. 2. 12.</hi> Theſe were the Duties taught by God to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles under the Law of Nature, and to the Jews under the <hi>Moſaick</hi> Diſpenſation; and afterwards refin'd, exalted, and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualized by our Bleſſed Lord, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon his Diſciples in all Ages under the Chriſtian. Theſe are abſolutely neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary
<pb facs="tcp:93911:4"/> for every Chriſtian Man; and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Allowances will be granted to our Weakneſs and Blindneſs, in the other World (which will be Anſwerable to God's infinite Goodneſs); yet I am ſure, there will be none for our impenitent Immoralities.</p>
            <p>This may plead my Excuſe for making <hi>Morality</hi> my ſubject, and then for that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular part of it which conſiſts in governing a Man's ſelf, I need premiſe nothing to what you will find in the following Papers; but that it is the Inſtrument of all the reſt, without which they cannot be exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and which therefore ought to be firſt learned. It virtually, at leaſt, contains all, or moſt <hi>Morality</hi> in it; and, if it were well practiſed, in all its Parts and Branches, it would ſoon abate the Spirit of Pride, Bitterneſs, and Malice which rages in the World; and teach Men, Love, Kindneſs, Sweetneſs of Converſation, Meekneſs, and Humility.
<pb facs="tcp:93911:4"/> It would make Men happy in themſelves, and happy in one another.</p>
            <p>Whilſt others therefore (My Lord) have been fiercely diſputing and wrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling about the Government of the Nation, the Humble Author hereof, ſitting un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Your Shadow in peace, thought it his greater Concern to turn his Thoughts inward, and ſtudy the Government of of himſelf; whoſe Meditations, from a very ſmall beginning, ſent to his Friend, have extended themſelves to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſions You here find them in; and, wrapt up in theſe Papers, are laid at Your Lordſhip's Feet, not ſo much to inform your Underſtanding, as to beg Your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection.</p>
            <p>My Lord, the Authour is ſenſible, and the World muſt confeſs, That You want not theſe Inſtructions. God hath given You and Your vertuous and happy Conſort (the true Partner of Your Joys and Griefs) the victory
<pb facs="tcp:93911:5"/> over Your Paſſions and Appetites; and having exerciſed You Both in an unheard of Affliction, hath now return'd in Mercy, and hath more than built up Your Breaches. All which hath (I doubt not) taught You to look upward to God in all his Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to look inward and govern Your Selves, and to look downward and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the World, keeping Your Self un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted from its Vices.</p>
            <p>Though therefore theſe Papers ſhould be of no uſe to You, yet if You ſhall honour them ſo far as to place them in Your Libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry among the Learned, and ſhall commend them to the Peruſal of my Young Lord, and the reſt of Your Children when they come to Years of diſcretion, and are fit to entertain ſuch Thoughts as theſe, the Authour ſhall have his End in this Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:93911:5"/>
            <p>May Your Lordſhip's Iſſue be numerous, and grow up like Olive-Plants round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Your Table: May They be Good as well as Great, and increaſe in Vertue and Piety ſo faſt, that They may anticipate theſe Counſels, and render all the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Arguments uſeleſs. Which is the dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Noble Lord,</salute>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Edlesb.</hi> 
                  <date>Jan. 12. 1690/1.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Lordſhip's moſt Humble Servant, and Chaplain, <hi>G. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:93911:6"/>
            <head>A Praemonition TO THE READERS.</head>
            <p>THO' the Form of this Eſſay is Epiſtolar, and was directed to a Young Gentleman in the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, as the Title informs you; yet the Author now, by its Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication, deſigns it for every Man, and deſires each Reader to imagine himſelf to be the <hi>Dorotheus</hi> therein mentioned. And though it concerns young Men eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (becauſe it ought to be their great Care, who are hereby prepared againſt a numerous Army of Fleſhly Luſts, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to aſſault them; and they of all Men ſhould lay a good Foundation of Vertue and Piety, and remember their Creator); yet thoſe that are aged muſt not think
<pb facs="tcp:93911:6"/> themſelves unconcern'd, unleſs they have finiſhed this great Work, or made ſome tolerable Progreſs in it: For as their Means are greater (having paſſed by the Importunities of Youthful Luſts, and ſeen their Vanity) ſo their Need is great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; having paſſed great part of their Journey, and ſo are nearer their End, and the Account they muſt give to their Creator.</p>
            <p>The whole was written originally for the Uſe of a Scholar, and ſo may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſmell too much of Univerſity Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; yet it hath been much allay'd for vulgar uſe: and if here and there it doth retain any Signatures of its original, yet moſt part is plain, and fitted for common Readers.</p>
            <p>The general Subject of it is, <hi>Morality,</hi> or the Practice of Vertue and Piety, which is the Eſſence of true Religion. And if there be any Notions in the <hi>Firſt Part</hi> out of the common Road, they were thought neceſſary, in the firſt draught, to give a tolerable account of the Reaſons of the Conjunction of the Two Natures in us, and of the Goodneſs of our Creator, in ordering it to be ſo: and they are ſtill
<pb facs="tcp:93911:7"/> retain'd for the ſame reaſon. And the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar Reader may (if he pleaſe) paſs them over to that which is more uſeful for him.</p>
            <p>The particular Duty explained and preſſed, he calls <hi>Autarchy</hi> or <hi>Self-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which is the reſtraining part of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, or the Power it has to curb our Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites and Paſſions. A Leſſon which he commends with ſo much Zeal, becauſe no Vertue can be long practiſed without it.</p>
            <p>The Way that he hath taken is inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive in the <hi>Firſt Part,</hi> and perſuaſive in the <hi>Two</hi> other: for it ſeems a natural Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, firſt to explain and then perſuade. And all <hi>Three</hi> are laid before every Man that will give himſelf but leave to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Wherefore he is ſent into this World? and Whither he muſt go when he leaves it? And the Author can only add his Prayers that they may have their Effect, in diſcovering the Fallacies of <hi>Senſuality,</hi> and in turning the Sinner from the Errour of his Way.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:93911:7"/>
            <list>
               <head>THE CONTENTS OF THE FIRST PART. CONTAINING The Nature of <hi>Autarchy</hi> (or <hi>Self-Government</hi>) and the Rules of its Exerciſe.</head>
               <item>THE miſerable Apoſtacy of Chriſtians in general, from the Practice of their Holy Religion. <hi>§.</hi> 1, 2.</item>
               <item>The Reaſon of this is the Predominancy of our Luſts and Appetites, and the want of their Regulation. <hi>§.</hi> 3.</item>
               <item>The Advantages of their Regulation, and the Poſſibility of it. <hi>§.</hi> 4, 5.</item>
               <item>The Deſign of the Author in order hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. <hi>§.</hi> 6</item>
               <item>Of the Two Natures in Man, the Spiritual and the Carnal. <hi>§.</hi> 7.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:93911:8"/>
               <item>Their Conjunction, and the Reaſons of it. <hi>§.</hi> 8, 9, 10.</item>
               <item>Why God did not limit our Appetites to Good only. <hi>§.</hi> 11.</item>
               <item>Their Contrariety. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Heathens account of the Two Nature<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>§.</hi> 12.</item>
               <item>What the Superiour Faculties require of us, and our Duty thereupon. <hi>§.</hi> 13, 14.</item>
               <item>What <hi>Autarchy</hi> is, and wherein it conſiſts. <hi>§.</hi> 15.</item>
               <item>St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s account of it. <hi>§.</hi> 16.</item>
               <item>The Excellency of <hi>Autarchy.</hi> It is a ſure Sign of a Child of God. The Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Perfection of all true Religion. <hi>§.</hi> 17, 18.</item>
               <item>Six Rules of <hi>Autarchy,</hi> adapted to thoſe that are not yet enſlav'd to the Tyranny of their Appetites. <hi>§.</hi> 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24.</item>
               <item>Some Conſiderations offered to the Habitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Senſualiſts,</hi> (who have liv'd long un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Slavery of their Appetites) in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to their Freedom. <hi>§.</hi> 25.</item>
               <item>A ſhort Commendation of <hi>Autarchy. §.</hi> 26.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:93911:8"/>
            <list>
               <head>THE CONTENTS OF THE SECOND PART. CONTAINING A Vindication of the Pleaſures of <hi>Autarchy,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>THE</hi> Preface. §. 1.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Religion founded upon Spiritual and Inward Advantages, and the Promiſes of the Life to come, and is not ſo concern'd in Weakneſs of the Arguments for its Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Pleaſures, which yet make it more acceptable.</hi> §. 2.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Complaints of the</hi> Senſualiſt <hi>againſt Religious Severities.</hi> §. 3</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>An Examination of the pretended Pleaſures of</hi> Senſualiſts. §. 4</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the Expectation of Senſual Pleaſures.</hi> §. 5.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:93911:9"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of their Fruition, and St.</hi> John'<hi>s Analyſis of</hi> Senſuality, 1 Joh. 2. 16. §. 6.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the Luſts of the Fleſh. Of Gluttony, Drunkenneſs, and unlawful Luſt. The Vanity of them.</hi> §. 7, 8.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Covetouſneſs.</hi> §. 9.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of Ambition.</hi> §. 10.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Shortneſs, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncertainty, and Diſſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of Senſual Fruition.</hi> §. 11.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The End of Senſual Enjoyments calamitous,</hi> &amp;c. §. 12, 13.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Pleaſures of</hi> Autarchy <hi>poſitively de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated.</hi> §. 14.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Its outward Pleaſures, and the Enjoyments of Regulated Senſe.</hi> §. 15.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Objection from Poverty,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</hi> §. 16.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The inward Pleaſures of</hi> Autarchy, <hi>and how it has Influence upon the Soul.</hi> §. 17.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The inward Peace of the Soul obtain'd by</hi> Autarchy. §. 18, 19.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The pretended difficulties of</hi> Autarchy <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered.</hi> §. 20, 21.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the ſuper-additional Miſeries pretended to be laid upon all Pious Men. §. 22. to the End.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:93911:9"/>
            <list>
               <head>THE CONTENTS OF THE THIRD PART. CONTAINING The Outward Advantages of <hi>Autarchy.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <hi>THE</hi> Preface. §. 1.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the threefold Advantage of</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarchy, <hi>viz.</hi> A Healthful <hi>and</hi> Long Life, Competency of Eſtate, <hi>and</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect <hi>and</hi> Honour. §. 2.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of</hi> Health <hi>and</hi> Long Life, <hi>and the natural Deſire we have of it.</hi> §. 3.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>That it is the Gift of</hi> Autarchy, <hi>and that</hi> Senſuality <hi>deſtroys the Body.</hi> §. 4.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Objection concerning</hi> Mortification, Abnegation of the World, <hi>and the</hi> early Death of Good men, <hi>anſwered.</hi> §. 5.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the Second outward Advantage of</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarchy,
<pb facs="tcp:93911:10"/> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi> Competency of Eſtate, <hi>and</hi> Sufficiency of Riches. <hi>How</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarchy <hi>conduces to outward Riches.</hi> §. 6.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Objection, concerning the</hi> Poverty of ſome Good men, <hi>and the</hi> Wealth of the Wicked, <hi>conſidered.</hi> §. 7.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Two strange Effects of</hi> Autarchy, <hi>about Wordly Eſtates, that abundantly make Compenſation.</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Of the Third outward Advantage of</hi> Autar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, <hi>viz.</hi> A Good Name, Reſpect, <hi>and</hi> Honour. §. 8.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vice moſt diſhonourable, prov'd in ſeveral Inſtances.</hi> §. 9.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vertue and Wiſdom exalts Men.</hi> §. 10.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>An Objection prevented.</hi> §. 11.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Some other Benefits of</hi> Autarchy. §. 12.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Peroration and Review of all the</hi> Three Parts. <hi>Together with the Application to the</hi> Reader <hi>in ſeveral Particulars.</hi> §. 13.</item>
               <item>Autarchy <hi>not to be deferr'd or delay'd, upon Five Conſiderations.</hi> §. 14.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Serious Exhortation to</hi> Autarchy. §. 15, 16.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93911:10"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TARCHY:</hi> OR, THE ART of Self-Government.</head>
            <head>The Firſt PART.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>WHEREIN The Nature of <hi>Autarchy</hi> is Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd, and the Rules of its Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe laid down.</p>
            </argument>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <p>§. 1. THO' the Religion that the Holy <hi>Jeſus</hi> brought down from Heaven ſeem'd contriv'd by Infinite Wiſdom and Goodneſs, and adapted to render us innocent here, and happy hereafter;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93911:11"/> yet if you look into the World (into which you are, moſt dear <hi>Dorotheus,</hi> now ere long to enter, and in which you muſt live) you will find that moſt of thoſe that havereceived, and do ſtill zealouſly own this holy Profeſſion, do yet live in the greateſt oppoſition to it. Religion poſſeſſeth the Head, and not the Heart, and Men are mightily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned about its Doctrines, but not at all about its Duties. Its power over Men, as to the conformity of their Lives, is much weakned and decay'd, and the Spiritual Life ready to expire. Some Duties, 'tis true, are obſerv'd, out of Deſign; and its Out-ſide, for ſome political Reaſons, maintain'd; but if you draw the Curtain, and look into the in-ſide of Men's Practice, there is little but what is counterfeit and Repreſentations, Scenes and Shows. All the Noiſe that it makes, is from Men's loud Diſputes, and its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bandied backward and forward betwixt oppoſite Parties; but for any real Uſe that there is made of it, there is little, but that it is made to be a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:93911:11"/> ſtalking-horſe for Ambition; to ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie a bad Cauſe, and a cloak for its Deformity. Its holy Doctrines are ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenced and laid to ſleep; only now and then one taken up, and awaken'd to ſerve a Party, and then laid down a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, when no longer uſeful.</p>
               <p>Nor is the Law of <hi>Chriſt</hi> only (the Perfection of all Laws) but that of Nature and common Equity alſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated amongſt us. Property and Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhneſs hath ingroſſed all Hearts, ſo that whatſoever can be got either by Fraud or Violence, and poſſeſſed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out danger of the Law, is counted our own; and what we account to be out own, we think we may uſe as we pleaſe. Indeed there is a rude notion of Juſtice among the Vulgar, but it is only pleaded when they think they are injur'd; and exerted when they are like to be Gainers by it: But as for Truth (a piece of Juſtice we owe to all Men) there is little or no regard to it (eſpecially in dealings); but Men ſwear, lye and diſſemble, and will maintain that there is a neceſſity ſo to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93911:12"/> do. Hence it is, that Oaths (which were of old Sacred) are now of no Validity; yea, and the common uſe of Speech, in bargains, is to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: Lying is become ſo clamorous, that it hath took away our Senſes, and we had as good be deaf and dumb as hear and talk among Men: And then for Charity (that God-like Vertue) the higheſt notion of it is quite loſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, and we never give but when natural compaſſion wrings it out of our hands.</p>
               <p>Mean while Ambition is reſtleſs, and rages ſo in the World that it over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns whole Kingdoms, and buries thouſands in their Ruines: and Pride (that reigns among all Sects and in all ſhapes) will not ſuffer us to know our ſelves, or be quiet with others: And beſides theſe, there is ſuch a deluge of inhumane Vices (for ſo I call thoſe that are unworthy of Man, and below the Beaſt) broken in upon us from Hell, that no Pen is able to deſcribe, no Vertue oppoſe: for Man is become the greateſt Enemy to himſelf, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93911:12"/> cruelly wounds his own Being; ſo that the Love of our ſelves can ſerve no longer as a rule to meaſure our Love to others by, and the <hi>Apoſtle</hi>'s aſſertion (<hi>No man ever yet hated his own Fleſh</hi>) ſeems not to hold in our times. In a word, we are ſunk below Heatheniſm, while <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Infidels</hi> upbraid us. Impiety hath over-run the World, and our bleſſed Lord's Prophecy is too much verified, <hi>Matt. 24. 10, 11, &amp;c.</hi> 'Tis time then that thoſe days ſhould be ſhortned, that any Fleſh ſhould be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; and that he ſhould haſten his coming, for he ſhall hardly find his Faith upon the Earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <p>§. 2. And yet after all, it muſt be confeſs'd that this general <hi>Apoſtaſie</hi> of the greateſt part of Mankind cannot be laid to the charge of God, or to any defect in revealed Religion. He hath fenced and cultivated his Vineyard, though it brings forth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wild Grapes, and hath us'd all means poſſible to ſave us but one, and that is ſuch an irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtible Grace upon all Men, which ſome have fanſied to be beſtowed upon
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93911:13"/> thoſe that are effectually called; ſuch I mean as would carry us to Heaven by force, and ſave us whether we will or no. His Precepts are holy and juſt, and require of us nothing but what is reaſonable to be exacted, and feaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be done: beſides, his Commands are certainly our Intereſt as well as Duty; they are ſuch as would ſettle Peace and Proſperity amongſt Men, reſtore the golden Age, and make e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Man happy with his Neighbour and happy in himſelf; they enjoin no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Love, Peace, Meekneſs, Long-ſuffering and Courteſie amongſt all men, and would neceſſarily baniſh Hatred, Malice, and revenge, and all the inimical Vices from humane Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety: And to render him happier yet, by Sobriety and Temperance they would ſettle Health in his Body, and Peace and Contentment in his Soul. All this the <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> doth upon great and precious Promiſes, both of this Life and of that which is to come, and upon Threats propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable to its Promiſes; by which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93911:13"/> Means, and by the powerful Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of thoſe appointed to this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, God hath ſecured to himſelf in all Ages ſome Witneſſes of the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Power and Energy of Piety; which like ſo many ſtars, adorn and enlighten our dark Times.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <p>§. 3. It may now be juſtly enquir'd into, why ſo amiable and reaſonable a Religion, ſo profitable to every Man, and ſuited to his true Intereſt, ſhould not have the ſame Influence upon all, and captivate every underſtanding? Why the ſame cauſe ſhould not have the ſame effect, and the ſame Means prove ſucceſsful to every one that uſes it? eſpecially ſeeing there is no fatal ſentence to the contrary, nor do any labour under eternal Fetters, which binds their Hands from receiving what is offer'd to them? One would think that the ſame advantageous Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don ſhould be embrac'd by every ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Creature, and the ſame Word prove alike; not the ſavour of Life to ſome and of of Death to others. And certainly the fault muſt be in our ſelves
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93911:14"/> only, and in the indiſpoſition of the Patient, which may produce contrary Effects: For thus, the ſame Heat melts down Wax and hardens Clay. Nor is this Indiſpoſition generally in our Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Underſtanding, but in our Affections. We all know the Will of God and our own Intereſts well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and accordingly we ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve upon a new Life, and perform our Reſolutions; but, alas! Man is not uſually Maſter of himſelf, and of his own Intentions. The Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that God hath ſettled in us is ſore ſhatter'd, if not quite diſſolv'd. His Vice-Roy (Reaſon) is under con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finement; and the Senſes ſeduced from their duty; the Appetites (like diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute <hi>Janiſaries</hi> in an <hi>Interregnum</hi>) do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineer and carry all before them; and the Paſſions, like the <hi>Mobb,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to ſettle the State, and make ſuch a Noiſe, that the ſoft Meſſages of Peace, though from God, cannot be heard: for, Firſt, Man is uſually brought under bondage to the Earthly part, and the higher Faculties captivated by the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93911:14"/> he is carnal and ſold under Sin, and ſo cannot do what he would: The Fall of <hi>Adam</hi> has weakned his ſpiritual Powers, and brought them down, ſo that they ſtand upon even ground with the lower Appetites; and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom and a ſlaviſh yielding up our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Freedom have made us abſolute Slaves to our ſenſual Part. And hence it is, that though we are convinc'd of the Neceſſity and Benefit of Vertue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and of Repentance after we have offended, and promiſe, and (perhaps ſincerely) intend to act accordingly, yet after all we fail in our Performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and break our Reſolutions. The next Temptation bears all our Vows and Faith away with it; we have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled our ſelves, and (being under a kind of Confinement) can promiſe much, but perform nothing. And then, Secondly, Senſuality being got into the Throne fortifies it ſelf there, with ſpecious declarations of the lawfulneſs of its Title; and poſſeſſes the poor deluded with the mighty hopes of its Profits, Pleaſures, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93911:15"/> Advantages. It repreſents the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of Eat, Drink, and be Merry, to the utmoſt advantage: It crys up the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity of ſinful Freedom, and is always inculcating the Severities and Chains of Vertue. It repreſents Religion, ſowre and auſtere, and draws her pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, like <hi>Magdalene,</hi> always weeping. By theſe her falſe Repreſentations, and the Echo's of the Appetite, poor Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon cannot be heard. Hence it is that we firſt entertain, and (by converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) begin to love, and then doat on, and at laſt eſpouſe our Vices, not to be ſeparated as long as the Body and Soul hold together. Thus we are fallen ſince we came into this World as well as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and <hi>Adam</hi> was not the only Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayer of himſelf and his Poſterity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <p>§. 4. In this Condition, 'twould be a great piece of Charity and Juſtice to reſtore the Captive Prince, and break thoſe Fetters wherewith the rational part is bound up; to reſtore the Man to that ſtate that God made and intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he ſhould live in; that the Soul might govern the Body, and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93911:15"/> Will the Appetite; ſo that he might live as a rational Creature, and act as one that is moved upon future Hopes and Fears, and not upon preſent Enjoyments without reſpect to the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Conſequences thereof: For, if the Man were but brought to himſelf, and to the uſe of his Underſtanding, Vertue and Piety would find as ready entertainment as now Vice doth. He would then exerciſe his Reaſon inſtead of Senſe, and conſider the end of viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Actions; the preſent Enjoyment and future Reward would be brought into the Balance, and Hell and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven conſider'd as well as preſent Earth. The Inclinations to ſin would be leſs forcible, and the propenſities of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which ariſe out of Appetites would draw but moderately, and tho' they had a proper Motion, yet they would ſubmit to the ſtronger Power of the firſt Mover. Righteous Reaſon would then ſit enthron'd, and give ſentence according to our true Intereſt preſent and to come, and the Will ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving once determin'd, whole Nature
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93911:16"/> would move forcibly towards the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; there would be no hanging back towards <hi>Sodom,</hi> or hankering after the Fleſh-pots of <hi>Egypt:</hi> Men would go on in Piety chearfully, and run the way of God's Commandments having their Hearts enlarged. 'Tis the Empire of the Soul, and the Power of managing the Body to our ſpiritual Advantages, with its attendant Deſires (whichin the enſuing papers I would to the utmoſt of my power contribute to) that can on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſtore Piety and Innocency to the World. For <hi>Autarchy</hi> is a preparation of the heart for Vertue, and cultivates, tills, and ſweetens this our ſpiritual Ground towards an Increaſe of many-fold.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <p>§. 5. Nor is this Leſſon ſo hard, much leſs inſuperable, but what is and muſt be daily practiſed in ſecular Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of this Life, ſo that we cannot be Men, or live without it. We cannot enjoy all things, and therefore muſt deny our ſelves many things: and what is done upon worldly conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, may ſure be done more eaſily upon thoſe that are ſpiritual, by how
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93911:16"/> much theſe are more conſiderable than the other, and God is more ready to ſerve us with his aſſiſting Grace in this his own Work. Beſides, this cannot be difficult to Youth, who having not contracted any inveterate habits of Senſuality, are more at liberty: Nor can it be unattainable to Manhood, who, having paſſed over the Vanities of Youth, commonly chooſe what is profitable; much leſs to Old-Age, who have now no delight in Vanities, nor pleaſure in them. Thus every Age hath its advantages as well as diſadvantages, that no Man may complain that <hi>Self-Government</hi> is abſolutely impoſſible. However let every Man of what De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree or Age, conſider that this Duty is neceſſary, not only to this Life, but to that which is to come; and that the Grace of God (that bringeth Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) teaches us that we ſhould <hi>deny all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodlineſs and worldly Luſts, and live ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent World.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <p>§. 6. This then (my <hi>Dorotheus</hi>) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my preſent work, the end of this
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93911:17"/> triple Eſſay, and the mark which each Diſcourſe aims at: I ſhall,</p>
               <p n="1">I. <hi>Explain the Nature of this Duty, and lay down the Rules of its Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>Vindicate it from the Imputations of Auſterity, Sowreneſs, Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and other the accuſations of Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuouſneſs. And if I act not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly defenſively but offenſively, and make now and then an Incurſion into the Territories of Senſuality, carry away her Pretences captive, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them to Contempt; it will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to the Eſtabliſhment of</hi> Autar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy <hi>in every Man's Heart, who ſhall be open to receive her.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">III. <hi>I ſhall conſider the outward Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of</hi> Autarchy, <hi>and ſettle her right to all things which are deſirable in this World. All which put toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will be a ſufficient Explanation and Defence of</hi> Autarchy, <hi>whoſe Cauſe I have undertaken. And this I ſhall include in Three Letters, which ſhall be as Three ſeveral Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93911:17"/> at the end of each of which the</hi> Reader <hi>may ſit down, reſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and conſider what hath been taught him.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <p>§. 7 I. To begin with the <hi>Nature of</hi> Autarchy, <hi>or</hi> Self-Government. That I may lay a good Foundation and view the Fountain of theſe ſweet and bitter Waters that flow from the ſame Compoſition; you muſt know, that as every Man is made up of a double Nature, the Soul and Body; ſo he may find in himſelf a twofold Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Apprehenſion, Underſtanding and Senſe; as alſo, of Inclination and Tendency, the Will and the Appetite; the <hi>Firſt</hi> proceeding from the Spiritual, the <hi>Second</hi> from the Carnal part; that truly Angelical, this common with us to the Beaſts below us.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Firſt,</hi> is the Heavenly or Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Part of Man, the chief Faculty of which is the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderstanding,</hi> which the <hi>Greek</hi> Philoſophers call <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the <hi>Imperial</hi> or <hi>Governing</hi> Faculty, becauſe its Office is to guide the blind
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93911:18"/> and heedleſs earthly Part, with its Luſts and Appetites, as the Rider doth the Horſe with Bit and Bridle, or the Mariner doth the Ship with the Helm and Compaſs. This is the coeleſtial Part, and directs us to deſire nothing but what is really good for us, both as to the preſent and future time; I mean, to fear our Creatour, keep his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, live vertuouſly and ſober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly here, and, conſequently, happily hereafter; and, for the attainment of future Happineſs, to deny our ſelves ſuch Pleaſures and Enjoyments as would in the end endanger it. Thus we are taught to abhor Poiſon, though made up in the moſt ſweet and delici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Potion: And even the Vulgar (though otherwiſe ſufficiently incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable thereunto) ſhall, upon theſe grounds, deny themſelves Mirth, Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, Jollity, and other Delights of the Body; and, inſtead of theſe, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply themſelves to Labour and Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, till they have made them habitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al; and this, not becauſe they hate the the firſt, and love the latter, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93911:18"/> they are ſenſible that their Purſe or Body will not hold out in their purſuits. And thus alſo the Chriſtian (governing himſelf according to the dictates of the Spiritual Nature, and acting as a rational Creature, upon Arguments drawn from future Hopes and Expectations, as well as from preſent good) abſtains from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſt Gains and unlawful Pleaſures, and bridles his Natural Inclinations to any thing that may offend his God or his Neighbour. And this he continues to do, till he hath at laſt broken a Feral Nature to the Bit and Bridle, and made a kind of Habit of Piety.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Second</hi> is the Senſual Nature ariſing out of the counter-part of Man, the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. This is the Terreſtrial Part, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ncites us to deſire preſent Pleaſure (or at leaſt that which ſeems to be ſo to us) without any conſideration of its Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents or Effects: For the brutiſh Part <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Man is the ſame with that in Beaſts; uncapable of the future Proſpect of Good and Evil, and fully ſatisfied with what is preſent. So truly Beſtial is this lower part of our Nature, that it admits not of Hopes or Fears, but tends greedily to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93911:19"/> Enjoyment. This is that Conduit, by which the Devil conveys his Temptations into us, and the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by which we deſtroy our ſelves: Hence it is, that we know no Moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the uſe of animal Pleaſures; but run into that Exceſs, from whence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds the dreadful Catalogue of Crimes which St. <hi>Paul</hi> enumerates as <hi>The Fruits of the Fleſh,</hi> Gal. 5. 19, 20, 21.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <p>§. 8. It may be here queſtioned, by ſome, (with more Curioſity, perhaps, than Profit, were it not that we ſhould be jealous over every thing that might eclipſe the Divine Goodneſs) Why th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ever Gracious and Merciful Deity ſhould infuſe the Pure Spirit, freſh, new-created, and immaculate into the defil'd Veſſels of the Body? Why ſhould he join ſuch <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſuch diſagreeing Natures, the Heavenly to the Earthly Vehicle, there to loſe not only its Glory but Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency? For what is this, but <hi>Mezentius</hi> like, (might <hi>Atheiſm</hi> object) to join the living and dead Bodies together, that the one might die leiſurely, but infallibly, by the Putrefaction of the other? or, to put an undefiled Virgin (innocent and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowing
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93911:19"/> of Sin) into the Stews, where ſhe ſhall meet with Temptations of all ſorts to ſollicite her Chaſtity, and from whence, morally, it is impoſſible for her to eſcape unpolluted?</p>
               <p>'Tis true, the Doctrine of the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Creation of humane Souls, and their Infuſion into Bodies, is obvious to theſe and other mighty Prejudices, as that of their Traduction is to greater; and therefore ſome thoughtful Men have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived a long-ſince-forgotten <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> of the Creation of all humane Souls, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Angels, and other inviſible Beings before that of the viſible, of their Lapſe from their Primitive Integrity (as likewiſe did the Angels, and Mankind after both) and (after a long time of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>activity) of their being ſent down to Bodies diverſly circumſtantiated ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their ſeveral demerits, there to grind in their Priſon-houſes till Time had worn out, and the Divine Pity for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given them their Crimes; till Grace and the Exerciſe of Vertue had reviv'd the Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial Fire, and the loſt Image of God in them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This is the <hi>Prae-exiſtentian</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which, (they ſay) would fitly ſolve
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93911:20"/> all the doubts about the Goodneſs of God in our Origination, and diſſolve all that Darkneſs that ſeems to obſcure the Face of Providence. I mention not this Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion becauſe I would oblige any Man to believe it, but for its Novelty as to moſt Men, and for its Ingenuity; nor would I perſwade you to it, if you can clea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Divine Goodneſs or Juſtice withou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it: For it is not only the Privilege of the Schools to diſpute, but of every Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an modeſtly to opine freely of things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defin'd by God and his Church. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſeeing this <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> receives ſo littl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Light from reveal'd Religion that it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> generally look'd upon as the Product o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Fancy, I ſhall endeavour to untie th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Knot in plainer Terms, and upon mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> allowed Principles; wherein I muſt ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> run back as high as the Fall of Angels.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <p>§. 9. When Heaven, by the Lapſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo many of its Inhabitants, firſt, int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a ſtate of Sin, and then, into that o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Puniſhment (bound up in everlaſting Chains againſt the Judgment of the grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Day) became ſomething empty, and the Coeleſtial Powers were reduced to a leſſer Number; it pleaſed the Creatour of al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:93911:20"/> things, in order to the filling up of thoſe Vacancies, to make a Race of Creatures of a mixt and middle Nature, a little lower than the Angels, and yet higher than the Beaſts that periſh: Man I mean, Partaker of both the Heavenly and Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Natures united together; that the Earthly Part might teach him Humility, to avoid the aſpiring thoughts, and ſo the Fate of the lapſed Angels; and that the Heavenly Part might exalt his Thoughts, and lift them up to God his Creator: As his Strength and Endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were leſſer than thoſe of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, ſo were his Failures leſs fatal than theirs: He was plac'd in a ſtate, (not of Condemnation, in caſe of diſobedience, as they were; but) of Falls and Reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries, of Sin and Repentance: His Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was not ſo high as theirs, leſt, if he fell, his Fall might prove (like theirs) Final; and yet high enough to make his Recovery a Work, not a Paſtime; and a Work of that Difficulty, to require the Help of a Divine Saviour. Thus his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Compoſition became his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dvantage; and his Earthly Part, with its attendant Luſts and Temptations, became acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93911:21"/> the Cauſe of all the Mercies he hath received ever ſince. To which I may add—</p>
               <p>That as he conſiſts of two oppoſite Principles, ſo each muſt have its peculiar Law or Inclination in oppoſition one to another. That of the Spirit and that of the Fleſh, each tending, as it were, to its proper Centre; the one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viting him upwards, the other down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards: For each Nature would be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compleat, without its attendant Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Fruitions to careſs it: The Spiritual would be as good as dead, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out its Intellect and Proſpect, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, Deſires of Future Good; and the Earthly part had as good ceaſe to be, as ceaſe to be ſenſible of Earthly Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. If we could not experiment the Delights of Seeing, Hearing, Taſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> how dull and flat would our Lives be? like a Play without Scenes or Intrigue, without the Paſſions of Love or Hatred, or any thing to move the Spectators. 'Tis then not only out of a Principle of giving each Nature its Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, but alſo for the Comfort of both, that God hath endued us with Senſe and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93911:21"/> Appetite, as well as Reaſon: For theſe take off the Acerbities of Life, and render it tolerable; they ſupport the Body and Mind under all the Preſſures that God lays upon both under the Sun. Without theſe Life would not be worth the Acceptance when proffer'd, or Preſervation when accepted of.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <p>§. 10. And that which perfectly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates the Objection againſt the Goodneſs of God, is this, That there is no neceſſity of Sinning intended to be impoſed upon us: for our Appetites and Paſſions are not ſinful in themſelves, nor directly and ſimply incite us to it; but by accident, when put in a Commotion and Rage, and when the Reins are looſe and broken, like the Horſes of the Sun, when a fooliſh <hi>Phaeton</hi> undertakes their Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which would otherwiſe bleſs that World with Light and Influence, which it now burns up: Or like the Blood in a ferment, that ſometimes deſtroys that Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy it daily nouriſhes. 'Tis their Nature, 'tis true, to deſire to be ſatisfied, and move ſtrongly towards that Object they would enjoy, (elſe we ſhould have no Love or Hatred) but they are deſign'd
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93911:22"/> for Subjection, and not for Government; to hunt after that Game to which illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated Nature directs them and to be call'd off, or haſtened when a Superiour Power ſhall think fit: For, when under ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they may become ſubſervient even to Religion it ſelf, and, like the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> they may be <hi>Hewers of wood, and drawers of water for the Houſe and Altar of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ought to ſatisfie every modeſt Enquirer, who, though he cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the exact reaſons of his own Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination (alas how ſhould he!) muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that he is not only fearfully and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully, but graciouſly made, and a Monument of God's Bounty and Mercy. That his Creator is good to him in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, as well as to all things in general; and that <hi>his tender Mercy is over all his Works.</hi> I have taken the more pains to remove this Stumbling-block from the Entrance of this Diſcourſe, which yet St. <hi>Paul</hi> doth in fewer words, with this ſhort unanſwerable Queſtion (for the Chriſtian <hi>Romans</hi> in thoſe times were not ſo full of Cavils as we are) <hi>Shall the thing formed ſay unto him that formed it, why haſt thou made me thus?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:93911:22"/>
               <p>§. 11. If it be further queſtioned, Why God did not limit our Paſſions and Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites when he firſt beſtowed them upon us, ſo as to make it not poſſible for them to hurry us into any Sin or Danger? The Anſwer will be ſhort and eaſie. We are made Men and not Angels, and placed in a mutable condition, capable of Bliſs and Miſery; and if God had ſo bounded our Appetites, that they were incapable of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, we ſhould have been in an Immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble condition, like thoſe confirm'd, bleſſed Spirits above; a Privilege that they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were not thought worthy of, till they had been tried, and had reſiſted the Temptations and Threats of <hi>Lucifer</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtate Angels.</hi> There is no free Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture but muſt have a time of probation, before it be rewarded or puniſhed. Our Life here is like the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s; we are led through the Wilderneſs of this World, attended by our Folly and our Fears on our left hand and our right, to prove us, and to know what is in our Heart, whether we will keep the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment or not. And when this time of exerciſe and probation is over, we are called off the Stage, and are either free'd
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93911:23"/> or condemned. Beſides, were there no poſſibility of Sin, there could be no Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and ſo no Reward as well as Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: For if there were no Tempter or Enemy, there could be no Trial, no Fight, no Victory, and ſo no Reward; nor could even a St. <hi>Paul</hi> have challenged his <hi>Crown of Glory,</hi> but upon the account of his having <hi>fought a good Fight, finiſhed his Courſe, and kept the Faith.</hi> No won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then that Man ſhould have Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies within him as well as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out; theſe ſerve to awaken his Care, make him ſtand upon his Guard, and <hi>fight the good fight of Faith.</hi> Thus the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had the <hi>Canaanites</hi> to be their near Neighbours, and the ſame Land (like Humane Nature) maintain'd two contrary Inhabitants.</p>
               <p>And as there was no League made to be betwixt theſe Nations, but a continual War, ſo there is between the two Natures in us; <hi>the Spirit wars againſt the fleſh, and the fleſh againſt the Spirit,</hi> which St. <hi>Paul</hi> elegantly deſcribes, in his own Name, under the Perſon of one unregenerate, and in the ſtate of Nature, in the ſeventh Chapter of the <hi>Romans.</hi> Indeed Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:93911:23"/> may, and muſt be taken; the <hi>Canaanite</hi> muſt be ſubdued and brought under Subjection. And though (to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the Parallel a little higher) all Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with the ſeven Nations were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden, and a total Abolition of their Name from under Heaven, was enjoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the firſt time; yet when the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites</hi> had once declin'd to favour their Idolatry, the Angel of God brings this ſorrowful Meſſage to <hi>Bochim, That</hi> now <hi>they muſt not be totally driven out, but remain as Thorns in their ſides, and their Altars as ſnares unto them;</hi> and this to prove them and try their Integrity: So ſince the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> and the degeneracy of his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, no laſting and final Victory can be obtained; nor can corrupt Nature be abſolutely rooted out, till <hi>Mortality be ſwallowed up of Life,</hi> and Death <hi>delivers us from the body of this Death.</hi> The Seeds of Vices muſt remain even in the Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate and the Fire of Concupiſcence, though allay'd of its Heat, and covered up in its Aſhes: For all that Piety can do in this life, is to keep it down, and make it a uſeful Servant; to regulate it, and render it beneficial to us. And as in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:93911:24"/> every Kingdom Plots and Cabals will be, and ſome Diſſatisfactions, Commotions, and Tendencies to Rebellion; ſo muſt the Man of God ſtand upon his Watch, and be prepar'd to ſuppreſs every Emoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; if he can break the ſtrength of the Foe, and ſcatter his troops whenſoever they make head, 'tis as much as God (whoſe Deputy he is) requires of him; and this during his whole Life, till Death (calling him off his Watch) relieves him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <p>§. 12. Of this continual War in Man, not only the Philoſophers of old, under the ſtate of Nature have taught much and excellently; but even the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Poets (the moſt ingenious, but boldeſt and worſt of Men, that durſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the <hi>Deity</hi> more vicious and bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh, perhaps, than themſelves) have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of it: And therefore, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their witty way of <hi>Allegory,</hi> they call'd the Higher Faculties <hi>Prometheus,</hi> and the Lower <hi>Epimetheus,</hi> and of them they tell us this pleaſant but inſtructive Fable. <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Heſiod.</hi> op. &amp; dies.</note> 
                  <hi>That,</hi> (once upon a time) <hi>this</hi> Prometheus <hi>ſtole Fire from Heaven (viz.</hi> Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Knowledge) <hi>to enliven the Man of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:93911:24"/> Clay that he had made; upon which</hi> Jupiter <hi>was very wroth</hi> (though I cannot under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand why, unleſs he were envious at Man's good, a Character good enough for a Poet's <hi>Jupiter) and ſent</hi> Pandora (<hi>viz.</hi> Pleaſures) <hi>a beautiful but deceitful Female, to</hi> Epimetheus, <hi>his younger Brother, with a fine Box or Veſſel as a Preſent;</hi> Promethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us <hi>foreſees the fraudulent malice of</hi> Jupiter, <hi>and adviſes him to ſend back his Preſent with the falſe Bearer of it, the one being as deceitful as the other; but</hi> Epimetheus, <hi>greedy of the Beauty and Jewels both, that he might at once ſacrifice both to his Luſt and Avarice, receives the Woman and accepts her Preſent; which when he had o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, out flew all the Evils both of Body and Mind, which have ever ſince afflicted poor Mankind.</hi> I have mentioned this Fable in a Serious Diſcourſe, becauſe the true Hiſtory of it ſeems to be the Fall of our Firſt Parents, and the Moral of it the State of every ſenſual, ſinful Man; of him, I mean, whoſe <hi>Epimetheus</hi> governs, and contrary to the Monitions of the Superiour Faculties, entertains the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, opens her Box, and lets looſe thoſe Plagues that muſt worry him.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:93911:25"/>
               <p>But, without a Fable, (though in one) <hi>Ovid</hi> brings in his <hi>Medaea</hi> thus complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Torture ſhe endured in this Conflict:</p>
               <q>—Trahit invitam nova vis, aliud<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> cupido, Mens aliud ſuadet; video melier a probo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, Deteriora ſequor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                  <bibl>Met. l. 7.</bibl>
               </q>
               <p>Which is almoſt in the ſame Words, and altogether in the ſame Senſe with that of the holy Apoſtle. <hi>That which I do I allow not; for what I would do, that do I not; and what I hate, that do I.</hi> Rom. 7. 15.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <p>§. 13. And now (after a long, but I hope not tedious, Diſcourſe of the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the two Natures, that make up our <hi>compoſitum,</hi> and the Reaſons thereof) 'tis but time to draw nearer that I chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aim at, and to let you know what your Superiour Faculties (or rather God by them) require of you: and this is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but the ſubjugating of your Paſſions and Appetites in order to your threefold Duty, to God, to your Neighbour, and to your Self. Whey prohibit you (in the <hi>Firſt</hi> place) all thoſe Pleaſures, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions, and Alienations of Mind,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:93911:25"/> which uſually obſtruct the Love of God, his Fear, and Honour. They forbid (in the <hi>Second</hi> place) all immoderate Deſires of Gain, which may tempt you to break the Laws of Juſtice and Charity, and will teach you to deny your ſelf thoſe things which ſtand in oppoſition to either. But their chiefeſt concern is (<hi>Thirdly</hi>) in the <hi>regimen</hi> of your ſelf (which is the ground of both the other) that you obſerve the great Duty of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and Temperance, be guided by your Reaſon, and that you be able to make Reſolutions and obſerve them when they are made.</p>
               <p>For theſe Ends and Purpoſes, as a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Creature and a Chriſtian, you are to ſettle in your ſelf this high Court of Judicature, and a conſtant, firm Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſubmitting your ſelf to its Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations. 'Tis a great Vertue to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve well, but 'tis a greater to be able in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violably to obſerve our Reſolutions. It is the greateſt part of Wiſdom, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires our utmoſt force and ſtrength to ſtick to a Reſolve well taken. This is indeed our common Failure, and yet he is not a Men that cannot do this: A Man
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:93911:26"/> cannot be juſt to himſelf who is uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant to his own Purpoſes; the Will ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally is the Follower of the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and it is as good (nay better) to be without an Intellect (as the inferiour Creatures are) than to ask her Advice and not to follow it. The only hindrance to this great Duty is the Importunities of Senſe, and the Pleas of Pleaſure, Profit, and corporeal Satisfaction. Let theſe be kept under and in obedience, and then you will be capable to obſerve this great and neceſſary Rule following. <hi>Reſolve on nothing but by the Advice of righteous Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and when you have reſolv'd once, let nothing in Nature be able to divert the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, but a countermand from the ſame Authority.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <p>§. 14. Whenſoever therefore you are invited to any Action contrary to the Laws of God or Man, your great care muſt be ſuppreſs and conquer that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and that as ſpeedily and zealouſly as you would Fire in your houſe, or a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion breaking out in your Kingdom; as tending immediately to the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the whole. To this purpoſe you muſt ſtop every wandring or wanton
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:93911:26"/> thought, every inconſiderate word, and every intended Action, (for ſurely if Words are to be conſider'd twice, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Grecian</hi> Orator's Rule, Thoughts deſerve one, and Actions three Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations) and bring it before the ſupreme Bar of Righteous and Impartial Reaſon. The Rules of Examination are the Laws of God and Man, which are, in reſpect of Morality, plain and eaſie: And here the Golden Rule (that general Director of all our Actions, among Men eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally) with which our Lord concludes his divine Sermon in the Mount, is of uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Uſe, <hi>Whatſoever ye would that Men ſhould do to you, do you even the ſame to them; for this is the Law and the Prophets.</hi> Matt. 7. If your deceitful Heart diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe the Action, conſult a rectified Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and apply this (<hi>Lydius Lapis</hi>) this Touch-ſtone to it, and the counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit will ſoon appear, and you may make a diſcovery. If you find it an <hi>Amalekite,</hi> ſpare it not for Favour or Affection; no nor upon the Account of Religion it ſelf, but utterly deſtroy it. Without a meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor, ſuppreſs both your Paſſions and Appetites whenſoever you perceive them
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:93911:27"/> to interfere with your Duty and lead you into any Sin. This is that which the <hi>Greeks</hi> call <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as if nothing were true Wiſdom but this. The <hi>Latins</hi> call it <hi>Temperantia,</hi> Temperance or Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The firſt of theſe (<hi>Wiſdom</hi>) is uſually taken in a larger Signification, and comprehends this and other Duties: The latter (<hi>Temperance</hi>) ſignifies, in common uſe, but a part of this Duty, the moderate uſe of Meats and Drink, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And therefore I have made bold to introduce two <note n="*" place="margin">Autarchy, Autocracy.</note> Words into our Language comprehenſive of the Duty I teach you, and which will include the <hi>Regimen</hi> of the iraſcible and concupiſciple Paſſions, I mean <hi>Autarchy</hi> and <hi>Autocracy,</hi> both which ſignifie <hi>Self-Government.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <p>§. 15. <hi>Autarchy</hi> then is no other but the exerciſe of that Power that the Soul hath over the Body, and the higher Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties over the lower Appetites in order to the Practice of Vertue and Piety: As it reſpects our Duty to God it is ſubſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient to Devotion, and, by its Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and holy Revenges upon the rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious Appetites, it performs the ſevereſt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:93911:27"/> part of the great Duty of Repentance. As it reſpects our Duty to our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, it repreſſes the Emotions to Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, and teaches us to know what is that which is ſufficient for us: It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates all Inclinations to Injuſtice, and obliges us to the Golden Rule; it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates the Swellings of Self-conceit, and <hi>Philauty,</hi> and conſequently keeps Peace amongſt Men; for Pride and Selfiſhneſs are generally the Cauſes of all Wars and of Quarrels, Diſſentions, yea and of all the Schiſms in Religion, of all the evil Words and invidious Actions with which fooliſh Mortals torment themſelves and others. And laſtly, in reſpect of our ſelves, it teaches us to meaſure our ſelves by juſt Rules and Proportions, and <hi>not to think of our ſelves more highly than we ought to think, but to think ſoberly:</hi> to judge meanly of our ſelves and of our own En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments and Deſerts (for we are, or may be too well acquainted with our own private Failures and Lapſes) and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably of other Men, becauſe we know not theirs; and thus it lays the Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Humility that great Chriſtian as well as moral Vertue. It repreſſes An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:93911:28"/> prevents Malice, and regulates the iraſcible Paſſions; and ſo is nothing leſs than Meekneſs and Lowlineſs, the two ſpecifick Graces of the Holy <hi>Jeſus.</hi> It quenches the Heats of Luſt, and defends us from thoſe Legions of Tormentors, that are Conſequents of it. It makes us to <hi>poſſeſs our Veſſels,</hi> the Body, <hi>in Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication,</hi> not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (as the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal words it) in the Paſſions of furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and unbridled Deſires. It guards us from Gluttony and Drunkenneſs, and (teaching the right uſe of Meats and Drinks) preſcribes the neceſſary Rules of Quantity and Quality. Briefly, there is no Vertue or Grace but what it labours for, and which doth not ſtand in need of its Aſſiſtance, and no part of Religion but what it ſerves.—And all this it doth by watching over the Paſſions, to prevent Tumult, and puniſh Inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; by keeping the rein in the mouth of the Beaſt, and the Appetites in due ſubjection. Thus <hi>Autarchy</hi> is <hi>Cuſtos Pacis,</hi> the Keeper of the publick Peace in the little World, the Defender of Vertue, and a Magiſtrate bearing the Sword of Puniſhment (where it governs) not in vain.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:93911:28"/>
               <p>§. 16. This is that Chriſtian Duty that St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls <hi>Mortification</hi> or killing <hi>of the deeds of the Body, through the</hi> help and <hi>power of the Spirit,</hi> Rom. 8. 13. in order to the Heavenly Life. And theſe Deeds or Actions of the Body which are to be mortified, are in another Place cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led our <hi>Members that are upon the Earth,</hi> Coll. 3. 5. becauſe the Earthly part uſeth them as Members of the Body of Sin, and operates by them: Of theſe he reckons there only the concupiſcible Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, when contaminated and ungo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned, as <hi>Fornication, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate Affection, evil Concupiſcence, and Covetouſneſs which is Idolatry:</hi> and the <hi>Iraſcible,</hi> in the eighth verſe following. This is the <hi>Crucifixion of the old man,</hi> [call'd ſo, becauſe we brought it into the World with us, whereas Regeneration and the Spiritual Life begin in <hi>Baptiſm] and the deſtruction of the body of Sin.</hi> Rom. 6. 6. This is <hi>the Crucifixion of the Fleſh,</hi> or earthly Part, <hi>with its Affections and Luſts,</hi> which he mentions to his <hi>Galatians,</hi> c. 5. v. 24. By all which words (viz. <hi>deſtroying, mortifying, crucifying,</hi> &amp;c.) he means no other than keeping the Body in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:93911:29"/> and the exerciſe of the Duty of <hi>Autarchy.</hi> To which purpoſe he gives you his own Example, 1 <hi>Cor. 9. 27. I keep under my Body,</hi> [by Faſting, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Spiritual Exerciſes] <hi>and bring it into ſubjection</hi> [to the Soul, the Heavenly Part, whoſe Office and Charge it is to govern], <hi>leſt while I preach to others, I my ſelf ſhould become a Caſt-away.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And indeed as this our <hi>Apoſtle</hi> laboured more abundantly than all the other; ſo were his Sufferings proportionable, both <hi>by land and water, of ſtrangers and of</hi> his <hi>own Country-men;</hi> yet his <hi>Autarchy</hi> or <hi>Self-Government</hi> was that which made him endure all, not only with Patience, but with Glory. He us'd his Body to ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, whihc made it become habitual to him; and amongſt all thoſe Preſſures that he underwent for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> (ſome of which he himſelf mentions, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.) thoſe he impos'd upon himſelf, (becauſe he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd them upon himſelf, and voluntarily choſe them) were ſo much the more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious. Thus he was crucified with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> before he was beheaded at <hi>Rome;</hi> and was made a Partner in his Sufferings, and conformable to his Death, though
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:93911:29"/> never crucified. Thus he was not only able to <hi>do,</hi> but <hi>to ſuffer all things, through Chriſt that ſtrengthened</hi> him; and his Conqueſt of himſelf firſt, made him more than Conquerour. This was the Original from whence the firſt Chriſtians took the Copy of all their Faſtings, Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, and other voluntary Severities they put upon themſelves: Exerciſes now quite out-dated, nay ridicul'd, and call'd ſuperſtitious by an impious Pretence to <hi>Chriſtian Liberty:</hi> Their Auſterities and Faſtings, their Penances and holy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venges, their Retirements and Self-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nials were only to diſ-arm the Enemy within, and to render the Fleſhly part unable to hinder their Courſe of Piety; and that which they all their lives aim'd at, and which we ſhould alſo (if we would be as happy as they) was only <hi>Autarchy.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <p>§. 17. This is not only the great duty and end of all Moral Philoſophy, and Practical Divinity, but a certain Sign of True Piety: Others are ſometimes falſe, ſometimes frivolous; this cannot deceive us. Men miſs commonly in the Notion of Religion, and, leaving the Eſſence
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:93911:30"/> of it, follow its Shadow, and doat upon its Counterfeit: For if a Man can but expreſs an outward Zeal, though it be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in compariſon of the <hi>Phariſaic</hi> Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of old for the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> if he can but look demurely, and counterfeit a Seriouſneſs; if he can pour out abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of bold talk about God (though it be hardly Senſe); lament the Iniquity of the times (that is, ſlander and back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite his Superiours); and ſanctifie all his Raillery with ſhaking his Head, a Sigh, or a Groan; if a Man can do this (I ſay) he muſt be a Saint, an <hi>elect perſon, holy and beloved,</hi> &amp;c. though, in the mean time, his Heart be as full of Extortion and Exceſs, as the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> thoſe paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Sepulchres, were of old; though he can give his Tongue liberty to ſlander, and his Heart to envy; though his Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons be untam'd, his Appetites unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd every where but in publicl. The truth is, <hi>Autarchy</hi> (when exercis'd for the ſake of Religion) is a certain Sign, and the diſtinguiſhing Property of a Child of God, and all other Signs are deluſive: no Man can be either religious or wiſe without it. For true Religion
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:93911:30"/> begins within, and ſubdues the Paſſions and Affections; is not clamorous, raſh, fierce or envious (as well as) not voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, wanton or unclean; <hi>The Wiſdom which is from above is firſt pure, then peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, gentle, eaſie to be intreated, full of Mercy and good Fruits, and without Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality or Hypocriſie,</hi> Jam. 3. 17. He that brings his Body with its Luſts and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites into Subjection to the Spirit, (ſo that he allows of nothing either unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful or inconvenient) he that endeavours above all to obtain a pure Heart, and a right Spirit, and to this end puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies himſelf as God is pure; that viſits the Fatherleſs and the Widows in their Affliction, and keeps himſelf unſpotted from the World (which is St. <hi>James</hi>'s Notion of <hi>True Religion and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndefil'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God</hi>); this Man (notwithſtanding ſome Errours in his Judgment, and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terodoxes in Opinion) can be no other but a Son of <hi>God,</hi> and an Heir of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: for they are <hi>Christ</hi>'s that have <hi>cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified the Fleſh, with the Affections and Lusts.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <p>§. 18. And as <hi>Autarchy</hi> is a ſure ſign, ſo it is the Foundation and Beginning of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:93911:31"/> all true Religion; whatſoever is not built upon this is founded upon the Sand, and will fall in time of Temptation: Profeſſion without this is like an Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtume, it looks red, big, and fiery, and is a mighty Pain to the Profeſſor, but within it is full of crude Humours and Impurities which will at laſt break out into an Ulcer. Nay I will go further, and venture to ſay, That it is not only the Bottom, but the Top of all Religion, and its Perfection. <hi>Go, ſell what thou hast</hi> (ſaith our bleſſed Lord to the Young-Man in the Goſpel, who bragg'd of keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the Commandments from his Youth up to that time) <hi>and give the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to the Poor, if thou wouldst be perfect.</hi> Try whether thou canſt deny thy ſelf and part with thy beloved <hi>Mammon</hi> upon the Hopes and Promiſes of Poſſeſſions that are above? Whether thy Soul or thy Body, thy rational Faculties, or thy Appetite govern in thee? Whether thou canſt ſo far conquer as to deny thy ſelf this World for the next? For if thou canſt do but this one thing, there will be nothing wanting, but thou ſhalt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come perfect, and <hi>my Diſciple indeed,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:93911:31"/>
               <p>And if <hi>Autarchy</hi> be ſuch as I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented it, no wonder that it ſeems hard: Difficulty puts a price upon Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and even Heaven would not be ſo, were it of eaſie Aſcent, and the acqueſt of every idle Drone. <hi>Autarchy</hi> is too great a Duty to be the work of every common Pretender to <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> and yet it is not hard but eaſie, eaſie to him that is reſolute and faithful to his beſt Thoughts, eaſie to him that is exerciſed therein; of which more (it may be) hereafter. In the mean time let this be your Comfort, That it is not ſo hard but it is eaſily pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticable, and that it makes all other Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties eaſie.</p>
               <p>And now to apply all this to your ſelf and all others (for whoſe ſakes I have thus at large traced the Hoſtilities origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally founded in our Nature and our Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thereupon.) 'Tis certainly every Man's Intereſt as ſoon as he comes to the ſtature of a Man, and to years of Underſtanding, to conſider what he is? and why ſent hither? that ſo he may lay the Foundation of a wiſe and honeſt Life, and give a good account thereof to his Creator. And that you may do this the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:93911:32"/> better, I will, in the Cloſe of this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, commend unto you and all other <hi>Readers,</hi> theſe Rules and Cautions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <p>§. 19. <hi>Firſt,</hi> You are therefore, in the firſt place, to maintain religiouſly the Rights of the ſupreme Judicature, and ſubmit to it: And this by a firm and fixt reſolution worthy of the Courage of a Man, acting according to the Dictates of his Underſtanding and not Senſe; for ſuch a Man will die, rather than deſert his Reaſon; but of this before, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent not therefore to any thing that your Reaſon condemns, either as unlawful or inconvenient, though ever ſo delightful or advantageous, let the Importunities of Senſe be ever ſo great, that of Friends ever ſo earneſt, or Example ever ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. Some Men are of a Nature, ſtiff, moroſe, and reſolute, not without a ſeeming Mixture of Pride and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt; theſe are hardly to be adviſed or perſwaded; and they would in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect be happy, if they could always take up the beſt Reſolutions, becauſe they are beſt able to keep them: Others are of a ſoft, eaſie, and baſhful Nature, apt to be perſwaded, and to comply with
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:93911:32"/> Cuſtoms and Counſels, though to the prejudice ſometimes of their Reaſon; they are loath to deny and afraid to diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blige, being too good Natur'd to ſtrive as well in Vertue as other things: The firſt are like hard Wax, not to be diſſolv'd but by Force of fire; the ſecond, like that which is ſoft, are apt to be work'd into any ſhape by warmth and kindneſs. Though the firſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly abhorr'd as an Enemy to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Courteſie and humane Nature; yet conſidering the Policy of the Devil and his Inſtruments, it were to be wiſhed that our Nature be not ſo ſweet and pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able as to ruine us, but had (at ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time eſpecially) ſomething of Sowreneſs and Moroſity. If therefore you find your ſelf too apt to yield and melt into a Compliance, you ought to borrow a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Boldneſs, Self-Opinion, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of others, to fortifie your ſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Seductions. The Queſtion is only whether you will be govern'd by your own Reaſon, or others Folly, and there is no queſtion to which of theſe you ought to adhere: even Shame and Modeſty have their Evils and Extreams,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:93911:33"/> and ſomething of Confidence is requiſite to Conſtancy; do not therefore diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage your own Prudence ſo much, as to ſteer after every pretended Mariner's di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, but purſue the Methods of your own Reaſon; let others do as they pleaſe, do you act according to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of your own Judgment, and take heed of being ſelf-condemn'd: For if you act conſcientiouſly, and according to your beſt Light, without any ſiniſter ends, I will not ſay you cannot err, but this I am confident of, That God will not condemn you if you do, tho it be much. I don't know but I may extend this Rule to Opinions and Controverſies in Religion, but at preſent I intend it of moral Actions in Oppoſition to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements of Senſe. 'Tis hard (you'll ſay) to take up, and harder to keep a Reſolution in oppoſition to the Sollicita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Pleaſure and Profit, yea and of a Man's Native Inclinations. 'Tis ſo, I confeſs; and yet ſure this would not prove ſo hard a Work, if you take care in the ſecond place to</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <p>§. 20. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Begin betimes to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due your Appetites, and uſe them to the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:93911:33"/> Yoke, from your Youth; you well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Example of bending a twig whilſt it is ſuch, and the Leſſon that is inculcated from thence of early Exerciſe. The Senſual part when reduc'd into ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection young, doth become tractable and obedient, and will grow ſo; whereas, when it hath gotten ſtrength it becomes reſtiff, and ſtubborn. You have not wanted either Education or Example; and if you had, you are young enough to begin this Glorious Work. It is, in my Judgment, an excellent Method to make now and then an Experiment upon your ſelf, in things that are lawful: deny your ſelf the Enjoyment of ſome Pleaſures for a ſhort time, which may be lawfully uſed at any time, eſpecially then when you perceive Senſe to become moſt importunate. By this Means you will make a tryal of your Strength; if you are foil'd it will be no Sin; if you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer you may know your own Strength, and keep that in ſubjection, which may at laſt prove your Enemy. And if there were no other uſe of the Faſts of the Church, I ſuppoſe this only were ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to commend them to practice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:93911:34"/>
               <p>§. 21. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Endeavour to ſupport your ſuperiour Faculties, and aſſert their Authority by Arguments drawn from the Nature and End of that Action to which you are invited; examine whether it be convenient, if not ſinful? or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome Evil may not be the conſequent of it? Some Actions are apparently good, ſo that we need not diſpute of them; others are evidently evil; but there are Actions of a third ſort, which are indifferent, and though they partake in their own Natures of neither good nor evil, yet (as they are uſed) they may tend to either; theſe are they that are to be weighed in the Scales, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions taken accordingly. Beſides, there are ſome Evils in diſguiſe, and plead Innocency, and thoſe would be brought under Examination and Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
               <p>§. 22. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Avoid carefully all thoſe things that abate the Strength and undermine the Government of your ſuperiour Faculties. Such as theſe are, prophane Diſcourſes, evil Examples, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch'd Companions, laſcivious Songs, and <hi>evil Communications which corrupt good
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:93911:34"/> manners:</hi> There is ſurely a kind of Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in theſe, and they are catching e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in ſome Conſtitutions; they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the Soul through the Ear, pollute the Mind, and propagate Vice like a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Peſtilence; they ſerve for no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther uſe but to emaſculate the Spiritual part, weaken her Powers, defile her Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, debauch the Mind, and ſet up Senſe in the Throne of Reaſon. But as the greateſt evil of all (which for a while diſables the whole Man, the Soul in its Faculties, and the Body with its Members) avoid Drunkenneſs. This is a Sin which (when in intenſe degrees) brings a kind of Death upon the Body as well as Mind, and ſo intermits the Exerciſe of both Judicatures; but every Tendency to it, more or leſs, undermines ſober Reaſon, ſlackens the Reins of her Government, blinds the Underſtanding, and by degrees caſts her into a deep ſleep; and, thus weaken'd, lets looſe the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines</hi> upon her. And though, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs there be different degrees of this Sin, and different Conſtitutions of Men, ſo that ſome are made more wicked by it than others; (and thus ſome excellent
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:93911:35"/> Natures may be free from its uſual At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants, the greater Crimes I mean, in the uſe of it;) yet no Man, I'm ſure, can retain his Wiſdom and Diſcretion. You cannot but remember the old Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb to this purpoſe, <hi>Inebriari ſimul &amp; ſapere ipſi Jovi non competit,</hi> Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs makes all Men Fools, moſt Beaſts, and ſome Devils: And what it naturally tends to, learn from the Mouth of the wiſe <hi>Solomon,</hi> who deſcribes its Effects ſo ſenſibly and truly as though he had tried it, and obſerv'd it often. <hi>Prov.</hi> 23. 29. to the end of that Chapter. Let your Intellect therefore preſcribe the Times, Methods, and Meaſures of your Feaſtings, Mirth, Diverſions, and Compotations; conſult not Senſe about theſe her near Friends, to whom ſhe is ſo much allyed, leaſt ſhe deceive and betray you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
               <p>§. 23. <hi>Fifthly.</hi> If, by the Importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the ſenſual Part, the Perſuaſion of thoſe falſly term'd Friends, or the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of others, you have been ſeduced to do any thing unworthy of your ſelf, and thereby have proved Rebel to your bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Part; upon the firſt return of your Reaſon, and the recovery of your Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:93911:35"/> from its Eclipſe (for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacous Body will ſoon remove, and righteous R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſon ſhine out again, and by its Light ſhew you your Sin): I ſay, then your great care muſt be immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to fall down upon your Knees, and humbly implore Forgiveneſs of your Creator, for this Offence committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him and his Vice-gerent. At which time you are not only to renew your Reſolutions of Amendment, and fortifie your ſelf againſt enſuing Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, but alſo to inflict ſome Penance upon your ſelf for your defection. This cannot but be pleaſing to Almighty God, when he obſerves how you not only paſs ſentence, but do execution upon your ſelf, and thereby anticipate his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: Beſides, it will prevail with the Divine Benignity, for a ſupply of extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Aids for the future; make you more circumſpect over your ſelf (when you know that you muſt ſuffer for it) and ſatisfie your own Conſcience of the Truth of your Repentance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
               <p>§. 24. <hi>Sixthy,</hi> and Laſtly, (becauſe in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things we offend all, and ſo muſt &amp; ſhall do, during this ſtate of Imperfection) above
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:93911:36"/> all things beware of the Habits of Vices, and that you do not give <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enſual Part (at leaſt) the uſual <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits (you know) of all things, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of Vice, ſtick hard, and are not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily removed. Senſuality a little encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged will grow ſtrong, inſolent, and play the Tyrant, and warm'd, with the Snake in the Fable, begins to hiſs, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Poiſon, and keep Reaſon out of doors; the longer we delay to humble him (which yet muſt be our Task, at one time or other, unleſs we reſolve to be miſerable for ever) the harder our work will be. And believe me, a Man beſotted to his Vices, or (in the <hi>Apoſtle's</hi> Phraſe) <hi>dead in Treſpaſſes and Sins,</hi> is, next the damned, the moſt lamentable Spectacle; and the direct way to this Condition, is to gratifie our Appetites ſo long, till we muſt deny them nothing; yea, and at laſt deſtroy Appetite it ſelf, by pleaſing it: And though this may ſeem ſtrange, yet 'tis the true end of all Debauchery; for Senſuality doth at laſt devour itſelf, and the inferiour Soul, if let alone (like the Worm in the Fruit) will become its own Executioner.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:93911:36"/>
               <p>§. 25. But this caſe is (God be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) not ſo common: Such a Man muſt have loſt all Senſe of Vertue, be fully reconciled to his Vices, though never ſo deſtructive, and reſolv'd on his own Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine: He muſt be deaf to all Counſel, hardned beyond all Impreſſions of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Conſcience: The Spiritual Life muſt be totally ſwallowed up of the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive; and he muſt be a hardned, impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent, and contented Sinner; content to loſe Heaven, and endure Hell. If he hath any apprehenſions of his Sin and Danger, he is not irrecoverably loſt, but may admit of Help. To which Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, I will, in the Cloſe of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, lay down theſe Rules for his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery.</p>
               <p>I. Let him be truly convinc'd of his Condition, his preſent and future Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, his unworthy, Beſtial, and Brutiſh Life, and the Sorrows to which he is poſting: For if he can be but made ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of his Condition ſo as to deſire Help, he is capable of it, and may have it. The Underſtanding muſt be clear'd, and the Will rectified, and the Man made throughly willing to be cured.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:93911:37"/> 
                  <hi>Wilt thou be made whole,</hi> ſaith our Lord to the impotent Man, that had lain at the <hi>Pool of Betheſda</hi> thirty and eight Years; and having underſtood his willingneſs, he received the powerful Command of, <hi>Riſe, take up thy Bed, and walk.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>II. Let him then leave off all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiaries to Vice, as Wine and Strong-Drink, and the Converſe, Company, and Society of thoſe Betrayers of Souls, (thoſe Panders for Hell) which have hitherto accompanied him into Debauch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery; and let him frequent the Society of Wiſe and Vertuous Men, who will direct and encourage him by their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Example.</p>
               <p>III. Let him call upon God, who is always ready with his Grace to aſſiſt Pious Eneavours; who <hi>gives liberally, and upbraids no man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>IV. Let him begin with the Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>works of Senſuality, deny himſelf in ſmaller Matters firſt, and retrench him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by degrees. If he can conquer in a little, he may be ſure to proceed; and the more he prevails, the more he ſhall be enabled, till at laſt he becomes <hi>more than Conquerour, and can do all things thro' Chriſt that ſtrengthens him.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:93911:37"/>
               <p>V. And for his Encouragement, let it be conſidered that the old habituated Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner's ſtate is not ſo deſperate, but that he alſo hath ſome advantages of Piety: his Luſts and Appetites, by continual fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are become tired, nauſeate, and, (by the decay) leſs importunate. His Heats are cooled, his Raſhneſs modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and Righteous Reaſon is ready to convince him, That all ſinful Enjoyments are but <hi>Vanity and Vexation of ſpirit,</hi> That <hi>the days are come in which he can find but little pleaſure in them:</hi> For a Young man may, in ſome meaſure, be excuſed, but an Old man cannot; becauſe even Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture joins with Grace to ſound a retreat; his Appetites are ready every foot to leave him, and he is fain to uſe Arts to keep them; his Luſts ſlight him and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him, and he hath nothing but a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful vitiated Will, and a polluted Fancy left, which yet makes him ridiculous, and expoſes him. His Luſts firſt ſeduced his Mind, and now a defil'd Mind is forc'd to careſs them; like an out-worn Miſtreſs once ador'd, now ſlighted by her old Servants. 'Tis but time, certainly then, to retire, when we can purſue our
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:93911:38"/> pleaſures no longer: when Providence hath taken away the Temptation, we ought not to make to our ſelves Images and Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows of that which hath forſaken us. This is the Order of Nature, and thus <hi>Days ſpeak,</hi> (if we would hear) <hi>and multitude of Years</hi> would <hi>teach</hi> us <hi>Wiſdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Let him endeavour to obtain a true Eſtimate of the different Pleaſures and Advantages, the Ends and Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of Vertue and Vice, and by comparing them together, become ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied how much better 'tis to live the Life of a good Man, and a Chriſtian here, and to be received into Bliſs hereafter; than to be a Sot, a Slave, a Fool, for a few days, and afterwards to be damned.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
               <p>§. 26. This is the great Truth which the two following Eſſays do endeavour to illuſtrate, and which, I hope, your Experience will one day convince you of. In the mean time, let me only tell you, That the <hi>Senſualist,</hi> for all his gay Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours and fine Shows, is but a poor miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Slave, and enſlav'd to that which every good and wiſe Man keeps in Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection; I mean his Brutiſh Part, his Luſts and Appetites. Whilſt the Man
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:93911:38"/> that keeps his Liberty, and rules within himſelf, that uſes Pleaſures as a Cordial not continual Nouriſhment, and takes only what will agree with his Spiritual Advantages; the Man that can learn and practiſe this ſhort Leſſon of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>Moraliſt</hi> of old, <hi>ſuſtine &amp; abſtine,</hi> ſuffer and abſtain; ſuffer with Patience and Reſignation what Providence lays upon thee; and abſtain from every thing which may be hurtful for thy Body or Soul: This mighty Man, I ſay, this more than Emperour, reigns a Soveragin in himſelf; is invulnerable and uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querable; <hi>he falls into no ſin, nor runs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any Danger,</hi> but is the Favourite and Care of Heaven here and hereafter. And thus much of <hi>The Nature of</hi> Autar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, <hi>and Rules of its Practice,</hi> with which I ſhall conclude the Firſt Part of this Eſſay, and am,</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:93911:39"/>
            <head>ἈΥΤΑΡΧΊΑ· OR, THE ART of Self-Government.</head>
            <head>The Second PART.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>BEING A Vindication of the Pleaſures of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarchy,</hi> compar'd with thoſe of <hi>Senſuality.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <p>§. 1. AFTER a curious Search in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Original of Corrupt Nature, the Reaſons of its Conjunction with the purer Spirit, and the Rules to make it ſerviceable to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which was the Argument of my
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:93911:39"/> former Diſcourſe (my Dear <hi>Dorotheus</hi>) you may perhaps think it unneceſſary to write a Second time, or add any thing to that Subject. And truly after I had finiſhed the Former Letter, I became in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinable to that Opinion my ſelf, till (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides my Promiſe) I had conſider'd, that it is eaſie to give, and hard to take ſuch Counſel, that <hi>Autarchy</hi> is the moſt diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, and perhaps in ſome Senſe, our on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Duty, and that Senſe will become importunate, eſpecially when it hath Health and Youth to be its Advocates. And truly when I find ſo few Men, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in their beſt Age, and moſt vivid Exerciſe of their Reaſon, able to tame the Wild Beaſt within, I muſt confeſs I cannot rigorouſly exact it of Youth. My Buſineſs therefore ſhall be in the following Papers, to work upon your Affections; I mean, to engage my ſelf in the Cauſe of the ſuperiour Faculties, and endeavour to convince you that they are not rigorous, nor exerciſe any Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny over us; but that by a wiſe and ſweet Conduct they would (if permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) gently and carefully pilot our cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed Veſſel through the turbulent Sea of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:93911:40"/> this World, to the Haven of Happineſs; and this not only when the Rules are drawn by Morality, but by the ſtricteſt Religion. If this can be made out, Self-Government will be your Choice not your Yoke, and you will find it your great Duty and greater Intereſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <p>§. 2. And becauſe there be ſeveral ſorts of Judgments as well as Conſtitutions, ſo that ſome will be convinc'd with that Argument, which others cannot Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend or count ridiculous: Leſt from hence, <hi>Autarchy</hi> and its Vertues ſhould be diſparaged, by a real or ſeeming poor Apology, I muſt here premoniſh you, that its Exerciſe doth not merely depend upon thoſe outward Encouragements which follow. Morality is our Duty and our Intereſt, though never ſo ungrateful; and its great Obligations ariſe from Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Promiſes and Rewards in this Life, and the Eternal Joys of the Life to come; and tho' ſhe were ever ſo ſorrowful, hir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſute, and Squallid; yet thoſe inexpreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Joys ſhe inſpires into the Soul in this Life, and thoſe ſhe reſerves for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſtate, are abundantly ſufficient to ſubdue any rational Underſtanding. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:93911:40"/> Afflictions themſelves may be elegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, when, being light and Momentary, <hi>they work for us a far more exceeding weight of Glory.</hi> The End makes Sufferings to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable; and we ſee in Temporals, Men are very willing to be ſick for future Health, to ſerve a ſevere Apprentice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip for a laſting Freedom, to labour, toil, and ſweat for an approaching Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt, and to hazard the dangers of the Seas for Merchandice, and of War for Glory: Theſe are common Practices, founded upon rational Conjectures. And why ſhould not Religion engage us upon greater and more certain Motives? The Arguments then that follow are not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary but <hi>ex abundanti;</hi> If they convince, they will ſweeten the Methods of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, reconcile the Sons of Senſe to Vertue, anſwer the Objections of the <hi>Senſualiſts,</hi> and remove ſome Stumbling-blocks that offend the Carnal minded; if not, know yet that Religion ſtands upon eternal Foundations, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains ſecure, as having no need of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Rewards; though it may yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſome encouragements and advances in Minds not ſo defecate and ſtript of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:93911:41"/> the World, as ours muſt needs be while we live with Fleſh and Blood. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Prejudices of <hi>Senſualiſts</hi> are ſo many, loud and clamorous, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd to that degree, that I thought it worth my time to ſearch into the matter, and conſider whether Piety makes all her Votaries in this Life moſt miſerable: For Men moſtly preferr preſent to future Comforts, and theſe ſhort Joys in a Vale of tears, to thoſe of the Regions of Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs which are above. If I therefore can demonſtrate, that Religion hath its preſent Comforts, and perhaps greater, and more ſubſtantial than Senſuality can pretend to; all theſe Prejudices will va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, and Men will entertain it for its preſent as well as future Reward.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <p>§. 3. And here I expect to meet with great Diſadvantages by reaſon of thoſe Prejudices, which ſeem to be congenite and twiſted into humane Nature; for the Pleaſure of Self-denial (which muſt accompany <hi>Autarchy</hi>) are look'd upon as a Paradox, and Men bear a kind of anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy to reſtraining Vertue; when it puts the Roins into the Mouth of Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, 'tis thought imperious, and its Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:93911:41"/> intolerable. We have a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Inclination to pleaſe our worſer part, which even a mortified St. <hi>Paul</hi> was forc'd to complain of; this is the common Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murer which looks back towards <hi>Egypt;</hi> and, like the Spies ſent to ſearch <hi>Canaan,</hi> brings an evil Report of that good Land; <hi>The Land</hi> (ſay they) <hi>is indeed good, but their Cities are walled up to Heaven, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by Giants, the Sons of Anak, to whom we are but as Graſhoppers.</hi> See how Fear augments things, and what <hi>Hyperboles</hi> Infidelity can fanſie to it ſelf, for <hi>the Walls were not ſo high, nor the Giants ſo terrible.</hi> Thus the <hi>Senſualiſts</hi> will deſcribe the Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denying part of Religion; 'tis confeſt (will they ſay) all things conſidered, that it were beſt if we could govern our ſelves, and reſtrain our Paſſions, and they are certainly happy that can obtain that Power, but the number of ſuch have been but ſmall; ſome ſelect Saints of old, who had, as it were, put off Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature, and were extraordinarily endued with Strength from above; but who amongſt us, and in theſe degenerate times of Sin and Death, can throw down the Strong-holds of Sin, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:93911:42"/> thoſe gigantick Appetites that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them? this would be to turn An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels before our time, and put off that Humanity, that we muſt at the ſame time carry about us. Nor is this War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare only difficult but painful, nay a kind of Death, <hi>to die dayly,</hi> I mean to morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie our ſelves, and kill all thoſe diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and tendencies to Sin implanted in us. 'Tis certainly a harſh Leſſon which our Lord teaches us tho' by way of <hi>Metaphor;</hi> to cut off an offending Hand, and pluck out a wanton Eye; by which is implied at leaſt (alas that it ſhould be ſo!) the Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty and yet Duty of Seeing and not Deſiring. For why have we Senſes gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us if we may not uſe them? or why have theſe Senſes any Influence upon our Deſires, if they may not be gratified? This is to exact an impracticable Work of us, and excerciſe a Tyranny that would juſtifie even a Rebellion: For we can never become ſo unkind to our own Inclinations as thus to mortifie them, and under pretence of Religion act a kind of Martyrdom. Alas! the Scripture hath expreſs'd this Work in frightful Terms; and <hi>Mortification, Circumciſion
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:93911:42"/> of the Heart,</hi> and <hi>the Death of the Body of Sin,</hi> are words that carry Terrour in them: Beſides, as though the ordinary Exerciſe of Religion were not bitter e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, God hath infus'd more Gall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it by his Dealing towards his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and Providence ſeems to exerciſe them above others with Afflictions. What means elſe thoſe Sorrowful Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, by which our Bleſſed Lord fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warns his Diſciples of Perſecutions which they ſhould ſuffer, and which his <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> St. <hi>Paul,</hi> ſeems to entail upon <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> it ſelf, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 12. That <hi>all that will live godly in Christ Jeſus muſt ſuffer Perſecutions.</hi> I will therefore (ſaith the <hi>Senſualiſt</hi>) lay aſide this difficult, this painful Work, and depend upon Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy for Heaven; for if God had expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed better things from me, he would have made me better. Heaven is, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, worth the purſuit; but 'tis an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate that may be long before it falls, nor know I whether all my Sorrown and Sufferings in the Pangs of the New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>birth, will at laſt entitle me to it.—Or if this Reſolution be too daring, I hope I may yet adjourn this bitter Cup, this
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:93911:43"/> painful Task to Old Age, which is the only time proper for Penance and Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification; Pleaſures will then be denied me by Nature, and then (and not till then) I will deny them. Appetite muſt at laſt ceaſe, and then I will reſolve no longer to gratifie it. It is beſt parting by mutual Conſent, and when my belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Vices and I can keep company no longer; then, and not before then, we muſt part for ever.—</p>
               <p>Thus pleads the <hi>Senſualiſt,</hi> and ſo puts off this neceſſary, this pleaſant work till Death comes and ſnacks him off the Stage, and then his Thoughts and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns periſh. Or if he lives to Old Age, his ſinful Habits are become inveterate and fixt beyond the poſſibility of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval; ſo that Age finds him and leaves him, a hardned and contented Sinner. All which (yea, and the puniſhments of the other World that follow after) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from this <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, this Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Errour, That <hi>Autarchy</hi> is a harſh, unpleaſant work, and her Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Tyrannical.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <p>§. 4. It is now therefore my Task to combate the <hi>Senſualiſt</hi> with his own
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:93911:43"/> Weapons, and in his own Way, and to vindicate the Duty that I commend, which is look'd upon as the ſevereſt in the <hi>Christian Religion,</hi> (being no leſs than <hi>Self-Denial</hi>) from the evil Report that Sin and Satan would needs fix upon it. To do this I conſider, That there are but two Qualifications that can commend any thing to our Obſervation; <hi>viz.</hi> Pleaſure and Profit: Pleaſure is the peculiar <hi>Dali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lah</hi> of yonger, and Profit of older Years. Theſe are the two boaſted Advantages of <hi>Senſuality,</hi> for which the deluded Wretch pawns both Body and Soul, and the only Spoils he can aim at. If I can therefore demonſtrate, That there are equal, if not better Pleaſures, and as much Profit to be found under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Spirit, as there is under that of the Fleſh; I have mine end, nor will the want of theſe be an Argument againſt <hi>Autarchy.</hi> This is the remaining part of my Task, and the Province that I have undertaken, which (though it look like a Paradox) I hope to perform with that Evidence, that to an under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and conſiderative Perſon, it ſhall reach even to a Conviction.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:93911:44"/>
               <p>The only thing I deſire of you (my <hi>Dorotheus</hi>) is to ſtrip your ſelf of all Prejudices, and lay aſide the Love of Carnality; to clear your Mind of all groſs Matter, and to conſider Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments abſtracted from your natural In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations to them, and as they are in themſelves; and thus qualified, I ſhall not fear to make you judge in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Controverſie, while I weigh the preſent Advantages of Vertue and Vice in the Balance of Reaſon, and thence e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince that <hi>Autarchy</hi> is neither ſo difficult or unprofitable a work as it has been hitherto repreſented to you: That the Spiritual part lays no heavy Burthens upon Mens Shoulders grievous to be born, but that <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s heavieſt Yoke is yet eaſie and his Burthen light. And this I ſhall do by examining the Pleaſures of <hi>Senſuality</hi> in the firſt place; and, ſtripping off its Paint and Garniture, compare them with the more ſolid and ſubſtantial Pleaſures of Vertue. And then, having made ſome ſuitable Obſervations upon the Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty and Miſery which are ſuppos'd to attend a pious Life, conclude the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of this Letter, and leave the other
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:93911:44"/> outward Advantages of <hi>Autarchy</hi> for the Subject of the Third Part.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <p>§. 5. I am not here oblig'd to maintain That there are no ſuch things as ſinful Pleaſures, no more than with the <hi>Stoick</hi> deny that there is Evil in Pain and Torture. I know very well, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever pleaſes is a Pleaſure, and that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Man is ſenſible of ſo much in ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual Enjoyments; nor am I for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying the Appetites, but for regulating them. This is that which I aſſert, and ſhall endeavour to evince, That the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of Senſuality are few, poor, and deſpicable in compariſon of thoſe which are to be enjoyed in the practice of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, (which is ſomething more than what I promiſed before) and, conſequently, That 'tis an abſolute cheat put upon us, when theſe are made an Argument for Debauchery. This will appear if we take, in the firſt place, a general View of the Pleaſures of Senſuality, and make as we paſs along particular Referen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
               <p>In every ſinful Enjoyment there are Three things to be conſider'd,</p>
               <list>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:93911:45"/>
                  <item>1. The Expectation.</item>
                  <item>2. The Fruition.</item>
                  <item>3. The End.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Each of which are pretended to have its peculiar Pleaſures, and therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve our particular Examination. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan with the Firſt of theſe, Expectation.</p>
               <p>And here I need not uſe many words; for every Man muſt be ſenſible to how great a height the Hopes of vain Man is rais'd by the Deluſion of the Devil and his own Fancy. The approaching Enjoyment is repreſented through a magnifying Glaſs, and ſeems great and glorious: The Bubble of Fancy ſtruts and looks big, and we expect migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty matters. <q rend="margQuotes">Could I but poſſeſs ſuch an Eſtate, or enjoy ſo charming a fair One, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> Voluptuouſneſs hath certainly two Faces, ſhe turns the Young Face, and ſmiles upon thoſe that expect her, but looks Old and Wither'd upon thoſe that have enjoyed her. Each Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of approaching Good is thought a Bliſs, which yet vaniſhes in the Embrace; ſo that if the Votary to Sin had ſo much Wit, he would ſtop at Expectation, and go no further. He
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:93911:45"/> might then indeed continue enamour'd with the Child of his own Fancy, and worſhip the Idol of his own making, without Remorſe or Repentance, when it is too late. But his Unhappineſs is, That the ſame Expectation which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludes him, urges him on to deſtroy it ſelf, and ſo to put an end to his Hopes and Fears together, by a nearer Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, which we call Fruition, and comes next to be conſidered.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <p>§. 6. <hi>Secondly.</hi> Expectation then being confeſs'd by all to be only an imaginary Good, ſwell'd out with Hopes and Fears, 'tis Fruition alone that muſt crown the <hi>Senſualiſt,</hi> and make him happy. But even Fruition it ſelf is experimentally prov'd to be ſo vain and empty, and next to nothing, to have ſo little of real Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, and ſo much of Cheat in it, that after a Man ſits down and calmly conſiders what he hath done, 'tis a great Queſtion whether he will not repent of his Credulity, rail at the Deluſion, and preferr even Expectation it ſelf to it. For he ſhall then find that he hath im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced a Cloud, and fiſhed all night for Pleaſure, but caught nothing but Shame
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:93911:46"/> and Sorrow; that he hath been notoriou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly cheated; and having ſown the Wind, <hi>he hath reaped the Eaſt Wind;</hi> that he hath purſued a Phantom, and having hunted after Vanity, hath at laſt overtook Vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Spirit: For, the Pleaſures of Senſual Fruition are indeed but Shadows of thoſe of Vertue, and want their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigorations and Comforts: They are as ſhort of theſe as the Image of the Sun, repreſented in a Mirrour, is of the Light, Heat, and Influence of that glorious Luminary. That this may ſenſibly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, I will endeavour to waſh off the Paint from the Faces of theſe Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feits, and examine the matter of Fact, and compare the Pleaſures of the Fruition of Vice and Vertue together; Inſtances will have here their Uſe, bring the Matter near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er the Eye and illuſtrate it. And, to this purpoſe, I will uſe St. <hi>John</hi>'s <hi>Analyſis</hi> of Senſuality, in his tripartite Diviſion, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that (1.) of <hi>the Luſt of the Fleſh,</hi> (2.) that <hi>of the Eye,</hi> and (3.) that of <hi>the Pride of Life.</hi> 1 Joh. 2. 16.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <p>§. 7. And in reference to the Firſt of theſe, Conſider ſeriouſly with your ſelf, and then tell me (if you can)
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:93911:46"/> wherein conſiſts the true Pleaſure of thoſe Vices, which we call Gluttony and Drunkenneſs; that Pleaſure I mean that is peculiar to theſe Exceſſes beſides and above what is found in the limited Uſe of Meat and Drink. Is it in the ſtuff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of the Body, or the vitiating of the Palate, in the diſtempering of the Taſte, or the diſordering of the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach? Is it found among the Ruines of the Underſtanding, or the Laxation of the Members? Surely no Man can take any true Pleaſure in playing the Fool or Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, or in turning Beaſt beyond the Example of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar.</hi> I never yet knew any Man that delighted in making Experiments upon himſelf, to procure a voluntary <hi>Epilepſie</hi> or <hi>Syncope.</hi> Men are not uſually ſo fond of the Image of Death! and yet this, and no other is the Drunkard's Fruition, which is yet ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accountable, that the poor deluded ſeems to be under a kind of Faſcination, to doat on that which muſt end in Loathing, if not in Sickneſs and Death. Sure I am there can be no Fruition in either, but the momentary Touch of the Meats and Drinks upon the Nerves of the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:93911:47"/> Tongue, and yet even this is not pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to Exceſs, but is rather an Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant of Sobriety. The Sober perſon hath generally the quicker Palate and moſt Delight, though with a Dinner of Herbs and Small-beer; and if any Man enjoys himſelf and his Friend, 'tis only He.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <p>§. 8. And then for unlawful Luſts, (the other Species of Carnality) I may put the ſame Queſtion, with as great, and perhaps greater Advantage. Where are the Pleaſures peculiar to the Fruition of unlawful Love? Or, what doth the Adulterer enjoy above, and beſides what is to be found in loving and lawful Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage? If there be any ſuch Pleaſures, ſure I am, they muſt be imaginary and next to nothing. And that you may make a true Eſtimate of theſe and ſuch like inferiour Enjoyments, I muſt let you know (once for all) that we deſcend therein much below our immortal part, and equal our ſelves to the Beaſts that periſh. Nay more, this way the ſilly Aſs may out-rival the Man, and the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure Goat be more happy than he; that you will find them much below your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:93911:47"/> if not meer Cheats, the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs of Debauchees, the Shame of Wiſe men, and the Purſuit of Fools; too commonly a Sin, and always a Shame, and the Sign and Cauſe of our Mortality. For the Propagation of our Like, both ſhews us approaching Death and haſtens it, and we diminiſh our own Lives to give Life to others. But be it what it will, I have nothing to ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, in reſpect of Morality, when it is regular; I mean, when the Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial Vow hath ſanctified it, and the Tranſmiſſion of our Nature hath made it neceſſary; the ſtricteſt <hi>Cato</hi> will then allow it, the modeſt and chaſt St. <hi>Paul</hi> command it, and the Spiritual part con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to it. This for the lawful Uſe of it, for which Nature hath provided animal Pleaſures proportionate to its ends; but if you can fanſie any other Pleaſures pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to the ſinful uſe of it (which ſure is ſomething hard to do) turn but your Eyes and Thoughts upon thoſe rotten Carcaſſes, thoſe walking Sepulchres, which Laſciviouſneſs hath made its Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs; ſee there the Relicts of its Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, when it hath exhauſted the Spirits,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:93911:48"/> darkned the Underſtanding, weakned the Senſes, and putrified the very Soul by the Contagion of the Body, not to be puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied but by the Flames of Hell: And when you have duly conſidered this, then let the Adulterer boaſt of his ſtoln Pleaſures. Theſe are the chief kinds of <hi>the Luſt of the Fleſh,</hi> which is the eldeſt Daughter of Senſuality.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <p>§. 9. <hi>The Luſt of the Eye</hi> holds the next place, by which I preſume St. <hi>John</hi> meant Covetouſneſs, whoſe right to Pleaſures comes next to be examined. And if thoſe I have ſpoken of, had great Pretences to great Pleaſures, I'm ſure, this hath none at all: For, Covetouſneſs is confeſs'd by all to be a wretched Plague, or rather a Madneſs; and the Man that is enſlav'd to it, ſeems poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs'd, and is rightly Term'd a <hi>Miſer.</hi> But (becauſe <hi>Money anſwereth all things</hi>) if you can imagine that there is any Pleaſure in looking upon Bags of Gold and Silver (that is, White and Yellow Earth) reflect a little upon the Fate of a <hi>Tantalus,</hi> and think what it is to have, and yet not enjoy, great Abundance. If there be any hidden charms in Cares and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:93911:48"/> Fears; in watching Riches, leſt they take wing, and flie away, or (in the beſt Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of it) in being honoured and feared; yet I'm ſure the Happineſs of <hi>the liberal Soul</hi> which <hi>ſhall be made fat,</hi> and the ſweet content of him <hi>that is ſatisfied with Food convenient,</hi> doth far ſurpaſs them all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <p>§. 10. The Oſtentations and vain-glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Boaſtings proceeding from the Fumes of Ambition is the <hi>Third</hi> kind of Senſuality in St. <hi>John</hi>'s Method. And here I cannot but think that the ſtrutting Gallant muſt be conſcious to himſelf of his own Emptineſs, and that he ſhould take little Pleaſure in cheating others, when he knows he doth but cheat him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. And for the deſire of being great I would fain know where's the Pleaſure of forcing a Man's Way through the Briars and Thorns, the Dark Methods of Secret Plots, and the Labyrinths of Infernal Combinations? When by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dangerous Steps he is arriv'd at the unſteady Seat of Greatneſs, and has put on the (<hi>Incendialis Toga,</hi> the) poiſonous Robe of Jealouſies and Fears; When he is hated by ſome, and feared by others, and made a common Curſe by moſt, Is
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:93911:49"/> this that which you call a ſtate of Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs? His Port deprives him of Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the diſtance that he muſt keep, renders his Life ſolitary and uncomforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and yet, (which is very remarkable) he is troubled with Company, and his At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants will not give him the Liberty of an Hour's Privacy and Receſs. So that indeed a great Favourite, a States-man, can neither be familiar or retir'd, nor can enjoy himſelf alone or his Friends in Company, but muſt be confin'd to the Bedlam of Buffoons and Paraſites. If this be then ſuch a Pleaſant Life, <hi>per me licet,</hi> let thoſe that will run the danger, enjoy the Benefit of being great and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, of breaking the wild Beaſt to an ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie Pace and Mildneſs; they had need to have Returns anſwerable to their Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. And yet after all, I will produce more Safety, Satisfaction and ſweet Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in a mean Eſtate, and among the Country ſhades, than in all their Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, we that move in a lower orb, look up and gaze upon Greatneſs with Admiration, and think a <hi>Phaeton</hi> a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Man becauſe he ſits ſo high, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:93911:49"/> ſo much Brightneſs; but alas! we know not what Furies carry him on, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> what Dangers attend him. Every Man is uneaſie in his own Condition, would be greater, and has a Tincture of Ambition, and that makes us not know our own Happineſs, even when we are poſſeſſed of it. In the mean time, did we ſeriouſly conſider the ſtate of Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, we ſhould find St. <hi>James</hi>'s deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Lives to be adapted to his: <hi>A Vapour, that appeareth for a little time, and then vaniſheth away:</hi> A Cloud, that looks gloriouſly towards the Sun, and by the Reflection of his Beams, carried aloft by a ſuperiour Influence, for a ſhort time, and then it diſſolves in Tears.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <p>§. 11. I have at large examined the Pretences of thoſe Three ſorts of Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualities, to that which we call Pleaſures, and, ſetting them in a true Light, have expos'd their Deluſions; ſo that upon the whole matter, we may juſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, That their Pleaſures are not ſo ſurpriſing and extraordinary; nor indeed have they any at all peculiar to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but what is common to Vertue and Moderation, or rather what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:93911:50"/> from them: For Vertue dwells in the Centre, and is the Original of all true Pleaſure; and Vice in the Extreams, where ſhe receives and reflects back ſome of the Emanations which proceed from the Middle; but has none of her own but what ſhe borrows or counterfeits. Thus (that I may uſe an apt Similitude) the Sun, from the Centre of the World, ſhines by its own Light, whilſt the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, as ſo many dark Bodies, are whited over, and ſhine by Reflection only.</p>
               <p>But becauſe this is not a common No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and obvious to every Apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I will beſtow ſome ſhort Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon the Vanity of Fruition, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of its Shortneſs, Uncertainty, and Diſſatisfaction; Appendages which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay it to that degree, that it is not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the purſuits of Good and Wiſe Men.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>Firſt.</hi> For, <hi>Firſt,</hi> every Senſual En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment is Momentary and Tranſient; It ceafes as ſoon as perceived; and, like the Lightning, is gone before we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of it. I have here a large Field of Diſcourſe before me, but I need not ſtay to confirm what is confeſs'd, and at
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:93911:50"/> the ſame time, lamented by the greateſt <hi>Senſualiſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is uncertain; we loſe it oftentimes in the Embrace, and it va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth in our Arms. The whole Life of Man is but an Aggregate of indiviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Inſtants of Time, and every one of theſe may rob us of it; the Revenge of <hi>Saul</hi> was prevented when he had got <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> even in his Net; and <hi>Herod</hi>'s Divinity vaniſhed in the midſt of his Adorers, when the inviſible Hand conſign'd him to Worms. Every day gives us Examples of the inconſtancy of Worldly Pleaſures, and we are commonly carried up aloft by them, and then let ſall, and ſo bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to pieces; thus <hi>Alexander,</hi> in the midſt of his Victories, Feaſts, and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs, was call'd off the Stage; and ſo was the Rich Man in the Goſpel, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his Deſigns of Eaſe and Fruition. Nay more than this, a vain and needleſs Fear deſtroys all our Enjoyments, and they are ſo much the Creatures of Fancy, that they vaniſh and diſappear, upon the leaſt alteration of it.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It is at beſt but diſſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; every Senſual Enjoyment is a cheat,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:93911:51"/> falſe as Hell, whoſe Intereſt it ſerves; and as Viſionary as the nightly Feaſts of Witches: As theſe imagine that they eat and drink, and yet ſtill find themſelves purſued by the ſame hunger and Miſery; ſo Voluptuouſneſs leaves us as empty as before, and raiſes a greater Thirſt than it allays; nay more, it is loſt by U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, and the poor deluded loaths what he hath, admires what he hath not, is always to ſeek, and is never ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; he purſues an Aery Expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and courts a Miſtreſs, that when once enjoyed inſpires him with new Wants, and puts him upon freſh Queſts and Dangers. Thus the Slave to his own Luſts, rowls the ſtone of <hi>Siſyphus,</hi> and carried by the Gyre of his untam'd De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, moves an unconſtant conſtant Round, till Sickneſs or Age diſables him, and Death arreſts him, and carries him to the Infernal Priſons, where only he becomes Stationary.</p>
               <p>And thus I have made ſome Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon that Men call Fruition, or Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual Enjoyment. And I have been the longer, becauſe if there be any Pleaſure in Senſuality, it muſt be in this: By what
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:93911:51"/> has been ſaid, it will appear, That there is not a greater cheat impos'd upon Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, or rather that they impoſe upon themſelves: And I will be bold to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, That Sin begins and proceeds by Deluſion, and ends in Miſery; That Voluptuouſneſs is a Maſque acted by Furies in diſguiſe, which, towards the end, they throw off, and appear in their proper Shape. For this is the true End of all Sinful Enjoyments, which I muſt next demonſtrate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <p>§. 12. <hi>There is a way that ſeemeth right unto a Man</hi> (ſaith the Divine Preacher) <hi>but the End thereof is the ways of Death.</hi> Prov. 14. 12. The End of Voluptuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is always calamitous, and that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly in this Life. Sin brings forth Shame and Sorrow, and forbidden En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments tend to the Deſtruction of that Body they are brought to gratifie. Thus Intemperance weakens the Appetite, and conſequently the Body: Thus Luſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cites <hi>Ammon</hi> even to inceſt, and then to hate even to Death, till Drunkenneſs and the Sword of <hi>Abſalom</hi> hath cut him off, and ſo put an end to both Paſſions. And as Sin, at laſt, brings a
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:93911:52"/> diſmal Cataſtrophe upon it ſelf; ſo each Crime hath its particular <hi>Nemeſis</hi> even in our own Conſcience. And I dare appeal to Experience, whether (when a Man's Paſſion is over, and he is at leiſure to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider calmly what he hath done) he feels not Shame invade him, and a natural Horrour dart through his Soul? Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he doth not run, as it were, from the Preſence of God (as <hi>Adam,</hi> his Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, did) as aſham'd of his Naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or ſow ſome thin Fig-leaves together, ſome poor Excuſes to cover it? Thus 'tis at firſt, till Conſcience is ſeared or lull'd aſleep, and ſo becomes ſenſeleſs: Cuſtom will take off the Dread of Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, and becauſe Vengeance ſeems to ſlumber, the hardned Sinner removeth it far out of his Sight; and yet for all this commonly Conſcience at laſt awakes and laying before him the things that he hath done, arraigns, and condemns him: the black Fumes of <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> which hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto have hid his Sin and Puniſhment, will at laſt withdraw; and the <hi>Deity,</hi> juſt and terrible, diſcover himſelf to his Soul, and then learn, from his own mouth, the Agony of his diſtracted
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:93911:52"/> Mind; when he conſiders that he muſt leave all his Pleaſures, Friends, and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, and be carried alone into the dreadful unknown Abyſs of Eternity! When he begins thus to queſtion with himſelf, What if now at laſt there ſhould be a God, which I have not only provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, but denied; a Heaven, which I have ſlighted; and a Hell, which I have not only choſen, but made it my Buſineſs, and taken pains to procure? What if this God ſhall meet me in the other World and convince me of his Being, by his Juſtice; in what a Condition ſhall I be then? Why, no worſe than eternally and irrecoverably miſerable! And is it ſo? I find then I have liv'd to a fair pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe! I have enjoyed ſome few ſhadows of Pleaſures, and ſuffer'd many real Griefs! I have been cheated all my Life time with Hopes, Fears, and Expectations, and found all at laſt both <hi>Vanity and Vexation of Spirit!</hi> And now I can perceive no glimpſe of Joy, no comfort to my Soul; but a Darkneſs, and Horrour, and the Expectation of a dreadful Sentence when I ſhall depart hence! But Oh ſacred Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue! and you hoſpitable Graces of Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:93911:53"/> and Innocence! who alone are able to baniſh theſe dreadful Apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and bring home in Peace, how have I ſlighted and deſpiſed you!—This is very probable to be the End of the Voluptuous, becauſe the nearer he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches to his Death, the clearer are the diſcoveries of his Miſery; yet I know very well that ſome die, as well as live, ſenſeleſs and unapprehenſive of future Danger; but then their Condition is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the better, becauſe their Deſpair as well as Puniſhment are transferr'd to the other World. The Rich man in the Goſpel was never the happier in Hell, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he perceiv'd it not, before he open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Eyes in its Flames!</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <p>§. 13. I have led you (my <hi>Dorotheus</hi>) through the Folly to the Miſery of Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuality; of living in Rebellion againſt the higher Powers of the Soul, and working Wickedneſs with Greedineſs. You may eaſily perceive, upon the whole Matter, That there is much Sorrow and very little Pleaſure in Debauchery, and that Hell ſtands at the end of it; That thoſe poor Pleaſures that are enjoyed, are little elſe but Cheat and Deluſion,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:93911:53"/> and at laſt leave us not only diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed but miſerable. Happy is the Man that can ſee through the Diſguiſe, and apprehend the Deformity and End of Vice. Happy is he, that by an early Conqueſt of himſelf and his Earthly part, makes himſelf capable of the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of <hi>Autarchy;</hi> of thoſe that are to be found in the Paths of Virtue and the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gimen</hi> of the upper Soul. And theſe are they which come next to be conſidered.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <p>§. 14. It was the wiſe <hi>Epictetus</hi> that reduc'd all Morality, and his Readings thereupon to theſe two words (mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the end of the former Part) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſuffer and abſtain. Theſe two infold the whole Duty of <hi>Autarchy,</hi> and regulate, at once, our iraſcible and concupiſcible Appetites. The <hi>Firſt</hi> of theſe tells us we muſt ſuffer Injuries, Reproaches, and Slanders patiently: The <hi>Second</hi> enjoins us Abſtinence, from Sin, I mean, and from all Occaſions and Appearances of it. Theſe two were the conſtant Doctrine of our Lord firſt, and then of his Diſciples; only he went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond <hi>Epictetus,</hi> refin'd and exalted theſe Duties, and made the firſt eſpecially,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:93911:54"/> (the hardeſt of the two) one of the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atitudes, <hi>Matt. 5. Bleſſed are ye when men ſhall revile and perſecute you, and ſay all manner of evil againſt you falſly for my Names ſake. Rejoice and be exceeding glad, for great is your Reward in Heaven; for ſo perſecuted they the Prophets, that were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you.</hi> The Conqueſt of our ſelves, the Exerciſe of Self-denial, and the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient bearing of Injuries, is a preſent Bleſſedneſs as well as a future: This cannot be diſcern'd, I muſt confeſs, by the moſt part of Mankind in a degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Age, which will admit of no Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs which is not carnal. We put Senſuality in the Chair, and make her. Judge of the Pleaſures of <hi>Autarchy;</hi> and ſhe will not fail (without all queſtion) to give ſentence on her own ſide, in her on Caſe; <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>Self-Government</hi> is a painful, and a miſerable ſort of Life. Whereas, let enlightned Reaſon be pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced on the Tribunal, and you ſhall hear (that which <hi>Solomon</hi> long-ſince noted, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to a <hi>Proverb</hi>) That <hi>her Ways are Ways of Pleaſantneſs, and all her Paths are Peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:93911:54"/>
               <p>I have already, I hope, ſufficiently proved, That there is no conſiderable Pleaſure appropriate to Senſuality, but what ſhe borrows of Temperance and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, and then diſhoneſtly claims to be her own; and, That her End is Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and Shame. This were enough to obtain my Point, and make <hi>Autarchy</hi> (the ſevereſt of all Vertues) much more eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible; but I ſhall proceed to confirm the ſame thing more directly and poſitively, and that whether we conſider thoſe Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures that are outward or inward, thoſe that concern the Body or the Soul. For though I have appealed from the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Senſuality, in this Caſe; yet I will admit of the Evidence of the Senſes, when not either diſordered or bribed into a falſe Information.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <p>§. 15. And here I dare challenge all the <hi>Senſualiſts</hi> in the World to ſhew, in all their boaſted Enjoyments, any thing equal to the Delights of Moderation; or any Delight that doth not take its Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal from thence: For Animal Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures ariſe firſt out of the Temperate uſe of Nature, and when they are us'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond this, they become weak, decay,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:93911:55"/> and die. Sure I am, that the Pleaſure of Taſting (and ſo of all the other Senſes) is more vivid, quick, and laſting, and conſequently greater, in the Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Perſon, than in the Glutton: De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchery feeds upon, and devours it ſelf by being gratified; <hi>The full Soul loaths the Honey-comb, but to the hungry even bitter things are ſweet:</hi> The frequent Uſe of any thing takes away its Pleaſure, and it dwindles to nothing. Expectation, Art, and Fancy may ſupport it for a while, but at laſt it dies, and is utterly loſt by Enjoyment; whereas, he that governs himſelf by Rules and Meaſures, reaps all the Delight that Nature hath provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for him: For, whilſt Riot makes Men dull, ſtupid, and inſenſible; Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration keeps up, and maintains the Vigour of the Senſes, and conſequently their Pleaſure. Thus Vertue takes the beſt Courſe to propagate Youth, and continue it; her Servant is not uſually dim, nor is his natural Force (by Diſorder, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) abated; ſuch is he, or ſuch would he be, if <hi>Autarchy</hi> might have its Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:93911:55"/>
               <p>§. 16. Nor can Poverty (<hi>Infoelix Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertas,</hi> as the <hi>Poet</hi> calls it, the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhappy Poverty</hi>) or Meanneſs of Birth or For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune diminiſh theſe; I mean, the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Pleaſures of the <hi>Autarchiſt;</hi> his Dinner of Herbs taſtes as well as a fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Ox upon the Rich Man's Table: He needs no Sauces to commend his Meat to his Palate, or Varieties to delight him; Hunger and a good Stomach makes his Food (be it ever ſo mean) pleaſant, and Nature ſupplies him with the ſame, or at leaſt as delightful, Rarities, as Art doth other Men. And here give me leave, a little to vary from my Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and make a ſhort digreſſion in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of that we call Poverty: For if we ſearch into things themſelves, and lay aſide the accuſtomary abuſe of Words and Titles, we ſhall find that Heaven's Bounty is not ſo unequal, nor that there is ſo much Difference betwixt Men, in reſpect of outward Bleſſings, as the World judges. For, <hi>Firſt,</hi> we are all equally Rich in the common Bleſſings of Nature, and the Heavens and Earth, with all the good things of each, are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon every Man: The Sun,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:93911:56"/> Moon, and Stars, and their Light, Heat, and Influence is every Man's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety; and the Hills, Rivers, Woods, and Plains, with all the other Varieties of Nature (Objects more Auguſt than Art can frame) are all expos'd to his View, to delight and ſerve him. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> The Great Man hath no more from all his Superfluities than the Poor Man from his Neceſſaries: All the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues in the World, will but allow the Owner Food and Raiment (his Family and Servants devour the reſt); and all his ſtately Buildings will but give him ſhelter from the Extremities of Heat and Cold; and the Poor Man hath that which affords him both theſe, and commonly with more Peace and Safety. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Greateſt Perſon cannot ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate his Riches to himſelf; but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Men, (even the meaneſt) ſhall (in ſpite of Covetouſneſs) ſhare with him: He may indeed look upon his Palaces, Buildings, Aquaeducts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and Admiration (and ſo may the meaneſt of his Servants; and Strangers with greater Admiration than either): He may call them his own, and pride
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:93911:56"/> himſelf in his Magnificence; but I do not ſee, but (to moſt Intents and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes) they are as much his Servants as his. Indeed there is this difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the legal Owner and others; he may paſs over his Right to others, and leave them his Heirs, (to he knows not whom) which another cannot. He hath the Care and Trouble of them, which a Stranger hath not; but as to the Profits and Fruits of his Poſſeſſions, though he hath the Firſt Choice, yet his Inferiours muſt ſhare with him, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy it to as good Effects as he.</p>
               <p>This that I have ſaid, is not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract from Worth and Nobility, but to comfort thoſe that are eſtemed the Drudges and Slaves of this World. We have all enough, if we could compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend God's Bounty and be contented. If we could but govern our ſelves, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulate our Deſires, we might be Rich e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: For then we ſhould prize the Muſick of the Birds, and value the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours of the Flowers, above artificial Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes; we ſhould think our ſelves load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Bleſſing of Nature, were we apprehenſive of them, and could we view
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:93911:57"/> them with an intellectual Eye; we ſhould then find the Bleſſings appropriate to a middle Eſtate, as well as thoſe of a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and though our Commons be not great nor coſtly, we ſhould find Satiety. This is not altogether alienate from the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject in hand; for it ſhews the outward Pleaſures of <hi>Self-Government,</hi> even in low Circumſtances, and that whilſt the Voluptuous ſtudies to gratifie his decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and out-worn Senſes, the <hi>Autarchiſt</hi> enjoys the Careſſes of Nature, and there can be no innocent <hi>Epicure</hi> in the World but only he.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <p>§. 17. Nor is the Influence of <hi>Autarchy</hi> confin'd only to the outward Senſes, but it reaches the inward; yea, and the Operations of the Soul alſo: For though the Soul be a Subſtance diſtinct, yet ſhe is much influenced by the juſt and due Temperament of the Body, and hath no Converſe with things without but by the Mediation of the Senſes. And though, according to the Notion of the <hi>Platoniſts,</hi> ſhe be impriſoned in theſe walls of Fleſh, and has no Liberty to walk abroad, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhe may look out of the Windows of her Gaol, till Death comes and unlocks
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:93911:57"/> the Doors, unlooſes thoſe Bonds that faſten her to the Body, and ſets her at Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty; yet, during this Life, ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts a kind of acquaintance with her Priſon-houſe, and a Love to her Fetters: She is courted, and ſometimes ſeduc'd by external Objects, ſhe pertakes of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, Fury, and loves Fondneſs; and forgetting her native Country, and her Heavenly Nature; doats oftentimes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on low and baſe Objects in this ſtrange Land. In this preſent Condition Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance opens and clears the outward Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, and Knowledge regulates her Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptive Faculties, and both theſe ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then and preſerve the ſuperiour Faculties; which ſhews her her Errour, and helps her to avoid it. Hence the Charms of Volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuouſneſs are diſſolv'd, her Inchantments ended, and the Soul recovers her primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Light and Purity. Thus the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding becomes enlightned, and the Candle of the Lord burns without the Interpoſition of the Clouds of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. Thus the Memory is purg'd of polluted Images, and made a Treaſury of ſuch uſeful Idea's as Nature firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd it. And thus the Will becomes
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:93911:58"/> regular; the Deſires limited to that which is good; the Heart pure; and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit rectified, from whence proceeds In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency and Peace, which is the ſpecial Gift of <hi>Autocracy,</hi> and deſerves our fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Conſideration.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <p>§. 18. What the Ancient <hi>Pythagoras</hi> ſaid of Piety in general, may be affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of <hi>Autarchy</hi> in particular, when he ſays it is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>A Peace in the whole Soul, with Cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> For Senſuality fills us full of Fears and Jealouſies, Expectations and Diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments; and is like the Lower World, the Seat of Storms and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts; whilſt Piety would render our Minds as the pure Aethereal Regions, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all Winds, Meteors, and Alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, quiet and at reſt. The Mind of a pious Man is a Heaven upon Earth, and preſages to what place he muſt aſcend: His meek and innocent Converſation produces outward Peace amongſt all (for who would diſturb him that wrongs no Man, nor gives any Offence by word or deed?) And as he is guilty of no Crime, ſo he fears no Danger, but is at peace with himſelf: No Heavy and Diſmal
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:93911:58"/> Clouds of Deſpair obſcure the Serenity of his Soul. His Mind is always tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, free from torrid Deſires, and fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen Deſpondings: He knows not the Terrors of a guilty Mind, and is ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of Fears, becauſe he is ignorant of Sin: His Conſcience is <hi>void of offence towards God and Man,</hi> and therefore un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der no dread from either: He is content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his preſent Condition, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore feels not Fear's Ague nor Envy's Conſumption: Briefly, he is in a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Calm (though in a ſtormy World) and whilſt others fret themſelves under their Load, and ſtruggle in their own Toils, he is contented with his Lot, and at reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <p>§. 19. Thus for the Concupiſcible; and then for the Angry Paſſions, he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns them alſo. Hence it is that Abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Railery move him not, and he diſtinguiſhes betwixt the effects of Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs (for ſuch he takes Rage to be) and the friendly Rebukes of a Wiſe Man: He hears the Taunts of the Scornful un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concern'd as he doth the Barking of a Dog, and only takes care that he be not bitten. He looks upon a diſſolute Tongue with pity, and is more troubled
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:93911:59"/> at the Commendations of ſome Men, than at their Abuſes.</p>
               <p>And certainly there is nothing ſo unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and ill becoming (as well as trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome); nothing that makes us more ridiculous, or that gives an Enemy great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er advantage, than unbridled Fury; nor can any Plague torment the Soul and Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and prey upon both, more than ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Malice: Whereas 'tis a God-like thing to forgive; It elevates us above hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature, may I not ſay above the Angelical? Beſides 'tis the trueſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to be able to pardon. To deſerve well, and yet ſuffer patiently without Reward, is a part of Greatneſs unknown to any but the <hi>Autarchiſt.</hi> To ſuffer wrong ſilently, and being injur'd to ſeek a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation. 'Tis more generous, ſure, not to ſeek Reward, but to receive it, and ſave our ſelves the trouble of purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that which will be forc'd upon us; for rewarded here or hereafter we muſt and ſhall be, as long as our Lord's Promiſe ſtands good, <hi>Rejoice and be exceeding glad, for great is your Reward in Heaven.</hi> And as there is a future, ſo there muſt be a preſent Reward, which
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:93911:59"/> is <hi>Peace and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> An internal Comfort, an ineffable Pleaſure which ariſes out of a clear Conſcience, which <hi>is a continual Feaſt:</hi> This is a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure far ſurpaſſing all the Riches of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and the Pleaſures of Sin, though dreſt up to the utmoſt advantage; for they are but for a Seaſon, but <hi>this ſhall not be taken away from us.</hi> Joh. 16. 22. <hi>Deny me (O Lord) Riches, Health, Proſperity, Liberty, or whatſoever elſe is moſt dear to the Animal Life, only deny me not this. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe me in what Trials, and with what Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions thou pleaſeſt, only allow me this Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial, and I ſhall be ſufficiently happy!</hi> This will be a ſufficient Compenſation for all Sufferings, and Support in them all: It will be a Light to guide us in this dark Sphere, and a Defence againſt all Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers: It is an internal Armour which will render us unconquerable, till we have paſt all the Perils of this World; and are arriv'd at Heaven, where con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd and never-ending Joys attend us.—For the proof of all which, I appeal to the Experience of every Man that hath been acquainted with Vertue and Piety, and obſerv'd their Effects: I appeal to the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:93911:60"/> Noble Army of Martyrs and Confeſſors, who ſuffer'd in their Quarrel, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came by this more than Conquerours. See then the different ends of Vice and Vertue! The Firſt preſents you with ſome Shadows of Pleaſures which prove both <hi>Vanity and Vexation.</hi> This Second beſtows upon you True Pleaſures, both outward and inward, ſolid and durable; which neither Pain nor Sickneſs nor Death it ſelf, arm'd with all its Terrors, can deprive you of; and which will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver forſake you, till they have brought you to that place where there is fulneſs of Joy and Pleaſures for evermore.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <p>§. 20. I have at large diſcours'd of the true Nature of the Pleaſures of <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuality,</hi> that cheat ſo many into their Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine; and, after an impartial Diſcovery of their Inſide, I hope I have ſufficiently expos'd their Falſhood, Vanity, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency. I have added to this an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect Account of the Pleaſures of a well-govern'd and vertuous Life. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect I ſay, for they are to be felt, not expreſs'd. I have nothing to add to this Letter, but ſome few Reflections upon theſe <hi>Two Heads.</hi> I. <hi>The Difficulties;</hi>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:93911:60"/> and, II. <hi>The Miſeries, that</hi> (in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this Diſcourſe) <hi>were objected to attend this Duty:</hi> And then conclude the trouble of this Letter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <p>§. 21. As to <hi>the pretended Difficulties of</hi> Autarchy, I have this <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. That <hi>Autarchy</hi> in it ſelf is neither hard nor ungrateful, but eaſie and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. Its Regimen was ſettled by our Creator in the beginning and firſt origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Mankind; and therefore not difficult to him who inſtitutes his Life according to the Order of Nature: For indeed all manner of Intemperance is a violence and rape upon our Nature, and we find that (till ſhe is conquer'd by long and cuſtomary Force) ſhe both ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hors and reſiſts it. Thus, for inſtance, Gluttony preſſes her down, and Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs ſtrives to ſtifle and drown her, whilſt ſhe (poor Wretch!) ſtruggles with all her force, throws up the uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocted load, the ſame way it was impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon her, and in reſentment of this Violence pines her ſelf ſometimes ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Days afterwards. This, I ſay, is the true ſtate of virgin, and unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch'd Nature. And therefore <hi>Self-Government</hi>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:93911:61"/> is her Guardian; nor can it be difficult originally, but natural, and conſequently eaſie. But then—</p>
               <p n="2">2. As it cannot be denyed, but that this among many other things is now grown difficult to us, ſo it muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd, That this Difficulty is the Effect of long and cuſtomary Habits of Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſneſs; nor can it be wonder'd, that a Man habituated to a ſinful Courſe of Life, and uſed to be carried about by his unruly Paſſions, ſhould find ſome uneaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the firſt entrance of a regular and ſtaid Converſation; no more than that an untam'd Horſe ſhould at firſt time regret the Bridle; or the young Bullock the Yoke that is laid upon his unaccuſtom'd Neck. All Changes, from one extream to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, prove troubleſome, and in every Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of Life we may obſerve the like. The beginnings of things muſt be diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, eſpecially to a prejudic'd Nature; and he that is accuſtomed to Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance muſt reſent a Reſtraint. The <hi>Neophite</hi> cannot but expect ſome trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the Government of his Paſſions and perverſe Nature; and the young Practitioner will be weary of his New
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:93911:61"/> Work; but he that has us'd himſelf to it, finds the Sweet of it; and he that is exerciſed therein ſhall find its De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And then, for thoſe affrightful Names of Mortification, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they were at firſt given with reſpect to the Removal of inveterate Habits, and the trouble it puts an old Sinner to. As for the things themſelves, they are not ſimply neceſſary to the Duties I commend, nor indeed to <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> no more than Phyſick is to our Mortal Bodies. Not ſimply neceſſary, but only by way of Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, and by reaſon of thoſe Diſeaſes of the Mind which we have contracted. When Piety begins to decay through the Weakneſs of the Powers of the Soul, and the Prevalency of the Appetite; then the Spiritual Pill becomes neceſſary; and if it be unpleaſant to the Taſte, or makes us ſick in its Operation, we may thank our Diſeaſed Minds for it. Corrupt hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours cannot be evacuated without Pain, nor can the dumb and deaf Spirit (much leſs that which is raging mad) be caſt out without ſore Convulſions of Mind, and a renting of the Heart, even to a ſeeming
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:93911:62"/> Death. But all this is but accidental to Religion, which in it ſelf is an eaſie Yoke, and a light Burthen; a ſweet and delightſome Imploy, and requires none of theſe Severities: For to a Man that hath been train'd up in Subjection to the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly part, and hath liv'd ſo till he hath become capable of ſenſing the Pleaſures of the Divine Life, there is no need of Mortifying of Luſts and Appetites; theſe have been regulated long ago, <hi>ab initio,</hi> bred up in Obedience, and taught Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from his Birth.</p>
               <p>I ſhall only add two things more upon this Head, and could wiſh that they might be as ſeriouſly conſider'd as they muſt be confeſs'd. The <hi>Firſt</hi> is, That the ſtricteſt Precepts of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> ſuch as Self-denial, and taking up the Croſs (the ſevereſt Doctrine of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereſt Religion) hath its peculiar Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and comforts, and that in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to its Hardſhips. <hi>Secondly,</hi> That Vice is the greateſt Slavery, and brings greater Mortifications and Hardſhips up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Body (yea, and upon the Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites themſelves) than the moſt reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Vertue, and conſequently that Men
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:93911:62"/> uſually take more pains, and ſuffer more to go to Hell, than is required in order to Heaven and a Bleſſed Eternity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
               <p>§. 22. As for the Miſeries that the Beginning of this Diſcourſe ſeems to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tail upon Piety, whether they are <hi>ab ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trà</hi> or <hi>ab intrà,</hi> I anſwer briefly,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That God is not ſevere or cruel to any Man, much leſs to his Servants. He is good unto every Man, and <hi>his ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Mercies are over all his Works: He is ſlow to Anger, of great kindeſs, and repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him of the evil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That he puniſhes them, or ſuffers them to be afflicted, ariſes out of other Cauſes; as, <hi>Firſt,</hi> To prevent Sin and the Doating upon this World, by letting them ſee their own Frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the World's Deceitfulneſs: To take down Temptations, and abate the Luſts of the Fleſh, <hi>&amp;c. Secondly,</hi> To puniſh Sin in this World, that their Souls may be ſav'd in the World to come. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> To bring them to Repentance, and recover their Spiritual Health. As a careful Phyſician, a ſevere School-Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and <hi>a loving Father who chaſteneth every Son whom he loveth, and ſcourgeth
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:93911:63"/> every Son whom he receiveth.</hi> And thus Afflictions are real Bleſſings, and the End changeth the Means into tokens of Love and Mercy. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> To make them In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the Divine Goodneſs. Thus <hi>Job</hi> ſtands a Monument, not ſo much of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Integrity, as of God's Juſtice and Mercy; his Juſtice in puniſhing his Creature, which, for all his Integrity, had ſome time or other deſerv'd as much as this; (and God may juſtly withdraw the Bleſſings of Health and Riches from <hi>Job</hi> which he had given him) and his Mercy in returning them double to him. Beſides, he is an ancient Example of the Power of Divine Grace, as alſo of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Imbecillity. And the ſame or the like Account may be given of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and the Firſt Chriſtians, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main Evidences of the great Love of God to Mankind, who ſpared neither his Son to procure us a better Covenant, or his Servants Blood to ſeal to the Truth of it. And therefore—</p>
               <p n="3">3. As to thoſe <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Matt. 10. 17. &amp; 24. 9. Luk. 21. 12. Joh. 15. 20. 1 Theſſ. 3. 3, 4. 2 Tim. 1. 8. &amp; 3. 12.</note> Texts where our Lord warn'd his Diſciples of Sufferings; or
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:93911:63"/> thoſe of his Diſciples to the Primitive Chriſtians, of the Afflictions and Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions which they muſt expect: They are not univerſarily applicatory; for their Caſe was extraordinary, and they were fitted with Divine Gifts according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And thoſe Texts do more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly point out thoſe calamitous Times, and cannot be applied to thoſe times in which the Church had peace and reſt from her Labours. Their work was in the heat of the Day, and God that call'd them to ſuch a mighty Work, firſt enabled them, and then crown'd them for it; but as for us, we labour in the cool, nor can we expect any Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition but that of our carnal Luſts and Appetites. Piety is commanded, and Vertue is encouraged and rewarded, and Religion is not now to be eſpouſed in Chains but upon the Throne. So that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the extraordinary examples of ſome of God's dear Servants in the Old Teſtament, and of many more in the New, I am bold to conclude, That <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarchy</hi> tends naturally and of it ſelf, to preſent as well as to future Pleaſures, whether it be of the Mind or a Regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:93911:64"/> Body, and to make us happy here and hereafter.</p>
               <p>And thus, having made what Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations and Reflections I thought ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble upon the Vanity of the pretended Pleaſures of <hi>Senſuality;</hi> having pleaded the Cauſe of <hi>Self-Government,</hi> and vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated it from the Acccuſations of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny or Cruelty over the Body or her attendant Paſſions, I will reſerve her <hi>Outward Advantages</hi> to be the Subject of the Third Letter.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:93911:64"/>
            <head>ἈΥΤΑΡΧΊΑ· OR, THE DUTY of Self-Government.</head>
            <head>The Third PART.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Of the Outward Advantages of <hi>Autar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy;</hi> and an Exhortation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
            </argument>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <p>§. 1. I had not long finiſhed the <hi>Second Part</hi> of this Moral Eſſay (in which, I hope, I have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what contributed to the allaying the Heats of your Senſual Deſires, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated your Prejudices to the Oeconomy of <hi>Self-Government</hi>) but I be thought my
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:93911:65"/> ſelf of my Promiſe made in the Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of it, to treat of the <hi>Outward Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages</hi> of <hi>Autarchy.</hi> 'Tis true (my <hi>Doro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus</hi>) the inward Pleaſures mentioned in my laſt, of Joy, Peace, and the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of a good Conſcience are the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Bleſſings we are capable of on this ſide Heaven; but then the other outward Bleſſings are not to be deſpiſed. As long as we are here we all naturally deſire thoſe Delights that careſs Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and he muſt be more than an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Philoſopher that can over-look all corporeal Pleaſures. He is happy that can gratifie his Soul, but yet he is thought more happy that can gratifie his Soul and Body both, and yet preſerve his Innocency. If then <hi>Autarchy</hi> be a Friend to both theſe, its Government ſure cannot be refuſed. What it is in reſpect of Pleaſures, hath been the Subject of the former Paper, and what it is in reſpect of all <hi>Outward Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages,</hi> ſhall be the Subject of this. After which I ſhall draw up all the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes into one concluſion; and, tying a Knot upon it, leave it with you to the judgment of after Experience.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:93911:65"/>
               <p>§. 2. The <hi>Outward Advantages</hi> of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarchy,</hi> which I have not diſcours'd of in my former, may be reduc'd to theſe <hi>Three Heads:</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. A Healthful and Long Life.</item>
                  <item>2. A Competent Eſtate, or Sufficiency.</item>
                  <item>3. Honour and Reſpect from all Men.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Theſe are the Three Principal Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites of the Body, and are courted as our greateſt Happineſs, while we are here. A ſickly <hi>long Life</hi> is therefore thought ſo much the more miſerable, becauſe it is long, and a <hi>Healthful</hi> Short <hi>Life</hi> miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by reaſon of its Shortneſs. And both <hi>Health</hi> and <hi>Length of Life</hi> cannot make us happy, according to the vulgar Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; if we are condemn'd to Poverty, and to eat the Bread of Carefulneſs. And there be many that will not be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied without a third acceſſional, I mean <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Reſpect.</hi> And there is no Man, but the higheſt Chriſtian, that can wholly lay them all aſide, and ſay, with St. <hi>Paul, That he counts all things but dung and loſs, ſo that he may win Chriſt.</hi> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expect you ſhould arrive at this Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Life, this Perfection of Wiſdom theſe many years. It will be ſufficient
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:93911:66"/> if you attain it at laſt with all the Aids of Morality, and Religion. In the mean time it will be ſufficient to alliciate a young and unexperienc'd Nature by that which ſeems moſt inviting in this World, (though it be but as Children with Toys, and ſuch are moſt of us in a ſpiritual Senſe) I mean with Earthly Bleſſings ſuch as <hi>Life, Eſtate,</hi> and <hi>Honour.</hi> My Buſineſs therefore ſhall be to demonſtrate to you (not that <hi>Autarchy</hi> will infallibly make you live long <hi>Healthful, Rich,</hi> and <hi>Honourable,</hi> or inſtate you preſently in the Poſſeſſion of theſe Three Bleſſings; for there may be many Circumſtances which may hinder the Effect, and God may not proſper the Means for the Ends deſigned: nor do I intend to affirm that this Duty will enfeoff you with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe degrees of each, <hi>i. e.</hi> that it will make you live to threeſcore years and ten or fourſcore, and all that while in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of outward Proſperity, Riches, and Grandeur; for this is not entail'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any Duty, but) That it is the readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Way, and the moſt probable Means to obtain a convenient portion of each, and enough to aſcertain an outward Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs:
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:93911:66"/> That it naturally tends to <hi>long Life,</hi> and <hi>Health, Sufficiency of Eſtate and Reſpect;</hi> and, where it is not hinder'd of its effect, will enſure them. Thus, as the Reaſons of the former Paper will make you a Votary to the Spiritual Government as a Chriſtian and a Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher, ſo thoſe of this may work upon you as a Man. I begin with the firſt of its Temporal Advantages, <hi>A Healthful and Long Life.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <p>§. 3. Of all the outward Bleſſings that God uſually crowns Man with in this World, <hi>Health</hi> and <hi>Long Life</hi> ought to be firſt named, becauſe moſt deſired. The Firſt begets the Second, and they mutually careſs each other, and would do ſo eternally. When things are as they ſhould be, Nature abhorrs an Alteration for fear of a Diſſolution. The ſullen Rocks cling together and oppoſe Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; and the ſoft Waters which are daſht into a thouſand pieces againſt them, reunite their Parts, which will not ſeparate till Gravity and the indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſible Laws of the Univerſe compel them. The Vegetables, though they die at Winter, do yet retain the Seeds of
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:93911:67"/> Life againſt their Reſurrection in the Spring, and accordingly appear again in their various Figures and Colours: The Birds and Beaſts labour night and day, to preſerve a belov'd though (to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) an unprofitable Life, and when they can no longer eſcape the Snares of the cunning Fowler or cruel Hunter, they mournfully utter out their reſentments of Man's Tyranny in their inarticulate Rhetorick. Man, the Lord of the viſible Creation, preſerves his own Life by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying others, and pays Nature in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf what he has robb'd her of in other Creatures. We are apt to admire the Happineſs of <hi>Methuſalah,</hi> and (if we thought it to any purpoſe) would deſire to live as long as he. We complain of Nature's unequal bounty to the Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diluvian World, whilſt ſhe confines us to Threeſcore or Fourſcore Years. To live long, and ſee many happy, or (ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than die) unhappy days; to live, though old, lame, decrepit, and deſpis'd (much more when young, healthful and ſtrong) is the univerſal deſire of deluded Mortals, inamour'd of their Sorrows and beſotted of their Chains: Nor can
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:93911:67"/> Reaſon, Counſel, or Experience (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Diviner Ray darted from Heaven into their Souls) undeceive them. And after all, it is ſomething unaccountable to find that, though moſt Men make <hi>Long Life</hi> the chiefeſt Petition in all their Addreſſes to Heaven, yet there are few that will confeſs they have received it, though they have paſs'd their great <hi>Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>max.</hi> So great is our averſion to Death, our greateſt Friend that would put an End to our Troubles, and lay us up in Peace. Young men put it far from them; and Old men do not care to hear of it, though deſcending down towards their Grave. And I have experienc'd in my ſelf, now entring into my Declinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a kind of Reluctancy to be told I was ſo far on my Journey: I conclude therefore that there is ſomething in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (ſome Relict of the Old man) that is afraid of Death, though ſhe carries it within her; and thus perhaps it will be with you, and therefore to pleaſe the lower Soul, and reconcile it to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the upper, I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to ſhew that it is the uſual Gift and natural Conſequent of <hi>Autocracy.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:93911:68"/>
               <p>§. 4. To this Purpoſe it will ſuffice to propoſe this one Conſideration. <hi>viz.</hi> That,—</p>
               <q>There is nothing that can conduce more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly to the Health of the Body (and conſequently to its Preſervation to Old Age) than the regular <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Meat, Drink, and animal Pleaſures, which <hi>Self-Government</hi> enjoins.</q>
               <p>This alone is able to preſerve Health, and to recover it when loſt, and (if ſome Original Diſtemper or fatal Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence interpoſe not) to convey it down to Old Age; to procure the Vigour of Youth in Age, and a healthful and ſtrong Conſtitution, and conſequently a <hi>Long Life,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>This Truth is ſelf-apparent, and ſhines by its own Light; for moſt Diſeaſes are confeſs'd to be the Effects of Intemperance. Vice tends to our Ruine from its firſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment; and the Body of Sin natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally leads us to the Body of Death. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes bring Sickneſs, and Surfeiting will turn to Choler. <hi>By ſurfeiting many have periſhed, but he that taketh heed prolongeth his Life:</hi> ſaith the wiſe Son of <hi>Sirach, Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſ.</hi> 37. 30.</p>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:93911:68"/>
               <p>Inſtances will beſt illuſtrate this Truth for their Conviction.</p>
               <p>For thus the Glutton lives to eat, not eats to live but to die; when by contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieties of Meats and Drinks he hath viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated his Appetite, and collected a Maſs of Crudities in his Stomach, the morbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick Matter which at laſt ſends him out of the World. Thus the Drunkard drowns himſelf in a Dropſie, or by a Collection of Adventitious Heats in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flames his Blood into a Fever; when he ſhall call for Drink without Satisfaction, and uſe it without Offence. And I wiſh it were ſeriouſly conſidered how peculiar an Enemy this Sin is to our Lives, and of how many ſad Accidents it is the cauſe, ſome times fatal to Body and Soul; of which we have too many Examples: So falſe is that flattering Proverb, <hi>A Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard never takes hurt.</hi> And indeed Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs is a kind of <hi>Daemoniaciſm,</hi> and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away the uſe of the Members of the Body, and Operations of the Soul; <hi>the evil Spirit caſts him ſometimes into the Fire, and ſometimes into the Water.</hi> Nor is it a wonder that when the internal Principle of Direction, the Underſtanding, is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:93911:69"/> the Guardian Angel driven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and kept at a diſtance, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil ſhould take the advantage to do a Man a Miſchief. In a word, Intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is ſuch an univerſal Purveyor for the Grave, that it is become long ſince a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, <hi>Plures gulâ quam gladio,</hi> &amp;c. The Throat is the greateſt Enemy as well as Preſerver to it ſelf, and deſtroys more than the Sword.</p>
               <p>Thus the impure Slave that with an Adulterous Eye purſues every Woman (beſides his Fears and Dangers) wears out his Body, and twiſts up his own Scourge. A Diſeaſe, I mean, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys his Form and Beauty, torments him with Pains when he ſhould take his reſt; makes him water his Couch with his Tears, and his Bed to be the Place of his Puniſhment, becauſe it was the Place of his Folly; and at laſt conſigns him over to Rottenneſs, and to become his own Sepulchre. And if Whoredoms and Adulteries do not always produce ſuch Tragedies, 'tis becauſe they are, in ſome Meaſure, reſtrain'd, and ſo it is the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of <hi>Autarchy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay thoſe immaterial Diſeaſes, thoſe
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:93911:69"/> of the Mind I mean, that are not ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant with groſs Matter, even theſe become prejudicial, if not fatal, to our Lives and Health. Covetouſneſs pines and withers the Body; Envy dries it up, and makes it pale; and Pride begets Quarrels, Contentions, and Wars, that ſend thouſands to the Grave together. I need not inſtance in more, for 'tis the Confeſſion and Complaint of emaſcula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Debauchees, that their Vices have been their Enemies, and contributed to their Deſtruction. So that there is a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Reaſon as well as Providence in the Sentence of the wiſe <hi>Solomon, Evil ſhall purſue the Sinner, and he ſhall not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long his days. Prov.</hi> 10. 27. &amp; 13. 21. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8. 13. 'Tis <hi>Autarchy</hi> alone that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes Moderation; that diſtinguiſheth betwixt the Abuſe and Uſe, betwixt the Poiſon and Nutriment of Meat and Drink; that maintains a due Temperament, and ſatisfies that Nature that ſhe preſerves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <p>§. 5. And here I cannot conceive what <hi>Senſuality</hi> hath to ſay for it ſelf, and in its own defence; unleſs it is by way of Recrimination: Unleſs ſhe leads you to the Cells of Aſceticks, and the Oratories
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:93911:70"/> of Recluſes, and ſhews you the pale and lean Effects of Faſting and Mortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; the Skeletons of ſome few Saints, who choſe to anticipate Death and die whilſt they lived. See there (will ſhe ſay) the Effects of Bigottiſm and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Frenzie, what ſhe would reduce the World to if ſhe could procure once a perfect Empire there! And what can Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xury it ſelf do more? Beſides thou mayſt obſerve that Wiſe men die as ſoon and as well as Fools, and the Righteous fall promiſcuouſly with the Wicked. Alas! Death makes no difference; nor can In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity, Wiſdom, Valour, or Parts op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him. The End of Man is deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd, and then why ſhould the Means be blam'd; he was to die at that time, and therefore why ſhould his Vices be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd for bringing him thither? Thus Sin is ready to excuſe it ſelf, though ſhe lays the Fault at God's door, and on his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Decrees.</p>
               <p>To all which I anſwer briefly.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>Firſt.</hi> Waving the Queſtion about the determination of our Lives (of which I ſhall find occaſion to give you mine opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion towards the end of this Diſcourſe)
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:93911:70"/> I ſay, as to the Hardſhips, Faſtings and Mortifications of reſtraining Vertue, I cannot find (as I noted before) that <hi>Autarchy</hi> abſolutely and univerſally pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes them, but only where our parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular neceſſities require them. God hath given his Creatures richly (though mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately) to be enjoy'd, and having gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us his Son, with him hath given us all things. But when the Beaſt within (the Senſual part) begins to wax fat, and kicks againſt its Maſter and Maker both; there is then but too apparent Symptoms of a Spiritual <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, an evil Habit of Mind; and then Faſting and other Ghoſtly Exerciſes become our Duty: For it is Phyſick to the Body as well as Soul, and ſerves mutually their Neceſſities. Beſides, I do not find any Command, even in that Caſe, to make our ſelves ſick, or to impair our Healths, for the ſake of Religion.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>Secondly.</hi> As for the Oratories of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſes, and the Cells of Anchorites, I know not where we ſhall find them in <hi>Europe,</hi> unleſs we travel to Mount <hi>Athos</hi> in <hi>Greece</hi> in queſt of them. And as for thoſe Multitudes in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:93911:71"/> that pretend to leave the World, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake the Vow of Coelebacy and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, moſt of them (I will not ſay all, for ſome Orders perhaps ſtill retain their original Strictneſs and Abnegation of the World: moſt of them I ſay) have miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably degenerated from the pretended Sanctity of their Founders. 'Tis true, there was ſuch a ſort of People of yore, and all Chriſtians were in ancient times extremely careful to keep themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted from the World, and ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps even to a kind of Superſtition. But this was then, when Religion poſſeſs'd the Hearts as well as the Heads of its Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors; and when the Breath of the Holy Jeſus was yet warm upon the Heads of his Diſciples and the Primitive Chriſtians. But, in theſe wretched times of Sin and Death, 'tis more than we can do to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade Men to a Receſſion from the World, in prohibited degrees and a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Converſe: and therefore this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance is (eſpecially with us) utterly impertinent.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>Thirdly.</hi> As for thoſe good Men that die Young: It proceeds not from any defect in <hi>Autarchy,</hi> but from other cauſes.
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:93911:71"/> Perhaps from ſome Native Diſtemper, which they receive by Traduction, twiſted up in their very Eſſence: From the original Weakneſs of the Contexture of their Bodies, made at firſt, and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Nature for a Tent, not a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Habitation for the Soul: Or, if the Pillars of the Body were ever ſo ſtrongly built up, yet ſome accidental Emergen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, ſome hidden Train may ſuddainly blow up the Fort; and God, by his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidential order of Second Cauſes, may concur to its diſſolution: Perhaps out of Judgment, as in the Inſtance of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient Prophet, that was ſent to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare againſt the Altar at <hi>Bethel,</hi> and <hi>in his return was delivered up to the Lion that ſlew him,</hi> 1 King. 13. Perhaps out of Mercy, when living well and longer are inconſiſtent, and when the righteous are taken away from the Evil to come. Theſe and ſuch like may be the Cauſes of the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Deaths of ſome ſober and regular Sons of Vertue, which yet their Temperate Life naturally tended to prevent. So that, notwithſtanding ſome particular Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, we may ſafely conclude, That <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuality</hi> is deſtructive to Humane Nature;
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:93911:72"/> which <hi>Autarchy,</hi> by its Rules and Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, would long preſerve; or in the Words of the divine Preacher, <hi>My Son, forget not my Law, but let thine Heart keep my Commandments. For Length of Days, and Long Life, and Peace ſhall they add to thee.</hi> Prov. 3. 1, 2.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <p>§. 6. The <hi>Second</hi> outward Advantage of <hi>Autocracy</hi> is, <hi>A competency of Eſtate</hi> or <hi>Sufficiency</hi> of the <hi>bona Fortunae,</hi> as we commonly call Riches. And when I have ſaid this, I mean not that it will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly and ſuddainly inſtate you with Abundance, or that there is no other way to become Rich; but that it is the only lawful way to a worldly Eſtate, and a probable way as well as lawful. It will defend you from Poverty, and feed you with Food convenient, if not with Superfluities: It is the proper and natural Means to obtain and increaſe an outward Fortune, and where Providence interpoſes not, it will attain that end. This muſt be confeſs'd by him that conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that it enjoins, 1. Parſimony and Temperance, whereby we become the beſt Husbands of what we have, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void all needleſs Expences, the Effects of
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:93911:72"/> Pride and Prodigality, and the Conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers of mighty Eſtates. 2. Juſtice and upright Dealing, which will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure us credit with all Men, and preſerve what we have gotten: For let Men take what Meaſures they pleaſe; yet they will not deny, but that Honeſty is the beſt Policy: For Juſtice doth attract the Love and Favour even of the Unjuſt; and upright Dealing will find a preſent as well as future Reward. <hi>With the ſame Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you mete withal it ſhall be meaſured to you again.</hi> 3. Care and Induſtry, which engage us by all lawful Ways, Means, and Meaſures both to get an Eſtate and increaſe it. For if we ſearch into the Cauſes of Want and Poverty, we ſhall commonly find Idleneſs or Debauchery at the Bottom of it; and moſt Men muſt accuſe their own want of Providence, not the Providence of God, for their Wants and Indigency. 4. Liberality, Charity, and Mercy, which are ſo far from being Enemies to Eſtates, that they augment them; for <hi>the liberal Soul ſhall be made fat, and he that watereth ſhall be watered.</hi> Prov. 11. 25. Beſides they call down the divine Benediction upon our
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:93911:73"/> ſelves and our Endeavours. <hi>To him that ſeeks the Kingdom of God, and his Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, all things ſhall be added.</hi> Matt. 6. And <hi>he that caſtes his Bread upon the waters ſhall find it again with increaſe:</hi> We may reaſonably expect <hi>to reap what we ſow, and receive by the ſame Meaſure that we mete to others.</hi> Luc. 6. 38. 'Tis our Lord's rule that cannot, will not fail, us if we do not prevaricate with our ſelves. <hi>Give, and it ſhall be given unto you, good meaſure preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed dowm, and ſhaken together, and running over, ſhall men give into your Boſoms.</hi> Nor can this Promiſe become ineffectual, but by our own Fault, our Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Hypocriſie and Infidelity.</p>
               <p>And now I dare appeal to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of any Man, whether there can be a more probable way to an Earthly Eſtate, than to be induſtrious in our ſelves, to have credit with others, and the Bleſſing of God to crown our Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours? And whether it be not as evident on the other ſide, that <hi>Senſuality</hi> makes Men Prodigal, Debauch'd, Spend-thrifts, Unjuſt, Fraudulent, Creditleſs, Unmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful and Cruel, and ſo to inherit nothing but the Curſes of Men, and the Vengeance of God?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:93911:73"/>
               <p>§. 7. But here I muſt walk cautiouſly, leſt the <hi>Senſualiſt</hi> take the Advantage, and prevent the uſual Objections which he will make to what has been ſaid upon this Head. It is confeſt therefore, that ſometimes all theſe means fail: That Vertuous Men continue poor, whilſt Violence, Oppreſſion, and Cheatery thrive and grow rich: For God hath his ſecret Ends and Purpoſes, and may make what Exceptions he pleaſes from this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Rule, <hi>viz. The hand of the Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent maketh rich.</hi> Prov. 10. 4. There is a ſecret Providence that orders every Man his <hi>quota:</hi> And thence is that which <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> obſerv'd long ago, <hi>There is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that ſcattereth and yet increaſeth; and there is that withholdeth more than is meet, but it tendeth to poverty.</hi> Prov. 11. 24. And yet this is no impeachment of the general Rule, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>Autarchy</hi> naturally tends to Riches, or at leaſt to Sufficiency. But if this be further preſſed (though I know no reaſon for it) I muſt not omit two mighty and almoſt miraculous Effects of <hi>Autarchy,</hi> which will ſufficiently ſupply that Defect and make a Compenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:93911:74"/>
               <p>1. The Firſt is that of making the Poor Man rich, above what Care, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, or the Philoſopher's Stone can do. For when God, for Reaſons beſt known to himſelf, denies him Abundance, <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarchy</hi> teaches him to ſupply that defect, by a willing Submiſſion to Providence, and a full Contentment with his ſmall Portion, as that which God ſees to be beſt for him: For he only knows what Meaſures are fit for us, and where to place the Two, as well as the Five and Ten Talents. Some Veſſels are not fit to be filled with ſtrong Liquors leſt they burſt, and every Man cannot bear the Temptation of Riches. God deſigns the Salvation of all Men in the firſt place, and to that great end proportions the Means thereunto. Theſe, and ſuch like Conſiderations make him ſit down fully ſatisfied with his ſhare, and thus at leaſt he is Rich, and <hi>having nothing doth yet poſſeſs all things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here I muſt tell you (my <hi>Doro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus</hi>) that it is not a great Eſtate that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways makes a Man Rich; for there may be great Poverty amidſt great Abundance. It was a ſore Evil which <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaw and
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:93911:74"/> lamented long agoe, <hi>A man to whom God hath given Riches, Wealth, and Honour, ſo that he wanteth nothing for his Soul of all that he deſireth; and yet God giveth him not power to eat thereof, but a ſtranger eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it.</hi> Eccleſ. 6. 2. And what is he better for that which he hath, or rather ſeemeth to have, who either not uſes it, or abuſes it? Or wherein conſiſts the Happineſs of that Man whoſe Riches are given him out of Judgment, not Love; and to be ſnares of the Devil, not helps to Charity? An Eſtate may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, I'tis true, by Fraud or Violence; but then it proves a continual Worm to the Conſcience, a Plague to the Mind, and a Conſumption to the Body. When a Father muſt run the danger of Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to convey an Eſtate, with a Curſe, down to his Son, and capacitate him to run the ſame Hazard; will you call ſuch a Man Rich and Happy? No, certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he is Poor, Miſerable, and a Wretch! whoſe miſtaken Love to his Son, hath induced him to ſell his own Soul to buy him an Eſtate, and made himſelf miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in the other World, to procure his Child a Shadom of Happineſs in this.
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:93911:75"/> Whereas he that can conquor his Deſires, and ſubdue his Paſſions; that is content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his honeſt Lot, is rich towards God, and communicative towards his Fellow-Creatures; That Man, I ſay, is richer than <hi>Croeſus</hi> the <hi>Lydian</hi> King, or <hi>Craſſus</hi> the wealthy <hi>Roman</hi> Subject.</p>
               <p>2. The Second is that of ſanctifying our Riches, and making it ſerviceable to our Eternal Concerns. A ſtrange Property ſure to convert Poiſon into Food; to heal the unwholſome Waters, and of the Snares of the Devil, to make a <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Ladder! And yet this is true: For our Lord tells us, that <hi>this Mammon of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs</hi> may be ſo rectified and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed, that it may and <hi>will procure us Everlaſting Habitations.</hi> And <hi>Autarchy</hi> alone (which forbids us to impriſon it in our Cheſts, or conſume it on our Luſts; but uſe it for our honeſt Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities) doth teach us this mighty Work. Thus <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Cable-rope is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twiſted to that fineneſs that it will perfo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the <hi>Eye of a Needle,</hi> according to <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ophylact</hi>'s Senſe of the Word; or elſe <hi>the Eye of the Needle</hi> is ſo expanded, and enlarged to that dimenſion, that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:93911:75"/> 
                  <hi>a Camel may eaſily paſs through it. Vid.</hi> Annot. <hi>in</hi> Matt. 19. 24.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <p>§. 8. The <hi>Third</hi> outward Advantage and Gift of <hi>Autarchy,</hi> is, A <hi>Good Name, Reverence and Eſteem with Men.</hi> And this is evident by the Reſpect and Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration which is given by the worſt as well as by the beſt of Mankind to Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue whereſoever it is found. Thus a ſober Perſon ſhall be rever'd by the moſt profligate, and the temperate admir'd (though envied) by the moſt debauch'd. The chaſt Virgins, who keep their Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence againſt many Temptations, ſhall at laſt be honoured as the Veſtals were of old; their very Company ſhall chill and quench the fiery Emotions of Voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs: for Vertue bears a Majeſtick Grace with it, whilſt Vice ſneaks into dark Corners: it carries a ſecret Awe with it, and checks the Attempts of <hi>Senſuality.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis true, there want not ſome, that from the <hi>Seat of the Scornful</hi> can ſcoff at Vertue, and ridicule Piety (the peculiar Talent and Character of the laſt and worſt of Times) but then, take notice, it is not when in its own Shape, but when
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:93911:76"/> miſrepreſented. They give it diſgrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Names, and dreſs it up in a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Shape, and then rally upon it. Thus Temperance is traduc'd under the notion of Covetouſneſs, and Piety is firſt term'd Hypocriſie and then expos'd as ſuch. The patient Man is ſaid to be a Coward; and the provident a poor nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row-ſoul'd Fellow: The chaſt is called coy and Proud; and the pious and devout is term'd ſuperſtitious and popiſhly affected. Thus Vice claps a <hi>Sambineto</hi> upon Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue before ſhe is to be executed; and, like her Primitive Votaries, ſhe muſt be deform'd in the Skins of wild Beaſts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore even the Dogs will faſten upon her. But otherwiſe it ſtands a univerſal Rule, that Goodneſs commands the Reſpects of all, and her God-like Majeſty ſhines even to the dazling of her Enemies: for ſo did her great Maſter's Divinity over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw thoſe that came to ſeize him, and the inviſible Rays of his Godhead dart them down backwards that came to bind him: Every one applauds Vertue, though few follow her: And all men call her Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, though ſhe has few that will imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate her. The greateſt Debauchee will
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:93911:76"/> commend her to be Guardianeſs of his Children after his Deceaſe, and while he lives condemn that in them which he practiſes in himſelf. This he doth while he lives, and when he dies, his Relations (if of Ability) build him a Monument and a Pillar, and record upon it all the good Works that he did, but none of his Vices. Hence are thoſe lying Epitaphs, and pompous Commemorations with which the Tombs of ſome are adorn'd, whoſe Names yet ſtink worſe than their Carcaſſes; and the Canonization of ſome Saints to Heaven, whoſe Souls are (I fear) long ſince conſign'd to Hell. This is Demonſtration ſufficient to convince us, that nothing can conſecrate our Aſhes, and give us a kind of Immortality here, but Vertue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <p>§. 9. On the other ſide, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more diſhonourable than Impiety, or unman-like than Sin. For inſtance: How ſhameful a thing is it to ſee a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, dedicated to the Service of God, ſtudy nothing but the Satisfaction of his Belly? For a Man made for noble Thoughts and Contemplations, to ſink below the Beaſts, and become a driveling
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:93911:77"/> Sot, and covetous of that which his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture cannot bear! To ſee the glorious I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God and Man both defac'd, his Beauty clean gone as well as his Reaſon, and himſelf a Companion to <hi>the Dog in his vomit, and to the Sow in her wallowing in the mire!</hi> To ſee a rational Being without Senſe, and a Man without Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, even beyond the Example of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How much below common Truth doth he deſcend that can ſwear to that, which his own Conſcience (at that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry inſtant) tells him is damnably falſe; or that can fawn upon him that he hates to death? That can dreſs up an Ape with gawdy Titles; and cringe, and bow to him, whom yet he will aſide call a gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en Aſs? How cowardly a thing is it to be forc'd to diſſemble hidden Treachery; to flatter an Enemy, and ſo take advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of his Security, that he may miſchief him in ſecret, whom he dares not meet publickly? How unworthy a thing is an inſidious Paraſite?</p>
               <p>What can be more ſordid, than for a Man of Reaſon, and a Profeſſor of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> (a Religion that exalts
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:93911:77"/> Reaſon, and directs us to the Angelick Life) to doat upon Gold or Silver, that is, white and yellow Earth; and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr a piece of Money to a Heavenly Vertue? What can be more fooliſh than to ſell a Man's Soul, (that is, himſelf) for a Bubble; or be condemn'd to the Galley all his life, that he may be ſaid to die rich? To be always fearing Want, in the midſt of Plenty; and to hanker after more, when he hath already more than enough? What more deplorable than to chooſe a Fever, that he may have the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of drinking and dying; to ſlave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for fear of Want, and die for fear of Death?</p>
               <p>What pity is it to ſee a Gentleman, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe compleatly endowed with the Gifts of Nature, to turn Slave to his Luſts, and Fop to the Humours of a Proud Woman? To ſee the Imperial <hi>Darius</hi> fawn upon <hi>Apame</hi> his imperious Concubine, and him that govern'd ſo many Gallant Men, govern'd himſelf by an inferiour Harlot? To ſee a Man for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake his loving Yoke-Fellow (that bears up one end of all his Cares and Fears,) and all the Pledges of their mutual Loves,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:93911:78"/> for the Embraces of a Strumpet, who loves him not but for his Money; who will firſt conſume his Eſtate and then his Body, and at laſt leave him to run the riſque of his broken Fortunes, not to be repair'd without freſh Sins and Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers!</p>
               <p>And, that I may ſay all in a word, to ſee a Chriſtian, made at firſt but a little lower than the Angels, and inſtructed in thoſe Myſteries which were hid from them; to ſee ſuch an one (I ſay) dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate below the Beaſts, and ſeek his chiefeſt Happineſs with the worſt of them! Thus every Sin draws after it the tail of a Serpent, Diſgrace and Shame; and no ſooner did it enter into the World, but it made the guilty <hi>Adam</hi> hide himſelf from the preſence of the God of Purity. Nor has it got any great repute (though many Followers) ever ſince. It is naturally aſham'd of it ſelf, bluſhes at its own Deformity, and uſually walks abroad in diſguiſe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der borrowed ſhapes, and better names to conceal it. Thus the Prodigal muſt be call'd generous, the Covetous provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, the Laſcivious complaiſant, and
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:93911:78"/> the Debauch'd a Good Companion. Thus Singularity and Faction were term'd Zeal; Diſobedience tenderneſs of Conſcience; and Murther, Rapine, and Ambition blended together, were call'd the Cauſe of God, and Reformation.—'Tis a hardned Sinner indeed that will not bluſh to hear in publick what he doth in private, and a patient one that will not highly reſent it: For tell but a common Harlot what ſhe is, and you move a neſt of Waſps; and the Adultereſs will take the advantage of the Law againſt you. Shortly, Every Sin is a reproach to Humane Nature, a diſgrace to Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and an indignity to the Order of the Creation. Sin and Shame are inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <p>§. 10. On the other part, (that I may look into the other Scale) Wiſdom ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alts them that are of low Eſtate, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motes them, and brings them to Honour. <hi>It lifts up the poor out of the duſt, and the needy out of the dunghil, that he may ſet him with Princes, even with the Princes of his People.</hi> It is a portion more precious than Gold; than the Onyx, Sapphires, and Rubies: It is the Original of all true
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:93911:79"/> Nobility, and ſupports their Titles and Dignities, which Debauchery would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, and ſo pulls 'em down into the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Vulgar. For Vertue is the true Nobility, the <hi>Palladium,</hi> or (that I may uſe a Chriſtian term) the Guardian Angel of Greatneſs: She enobles her Servant, and, not only himſelf, but his Poſterity; without this, Grandeur is but a ſwelling Bubble, a Cloud without Rain; or, rather, a blazing Comet that ſhines with borrowed Rays, and attracts the wonder of the Vulgar, and yet is in it ſelf an unlucky Omen to the World; and though its diſmal Effects may conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue long, yet it ſoon vaniſheth. Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom firſt founded the World, and hath preſerv'd it ever ſince, and as for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Governments of it, they have been all continued by <hi>Autarchy:</hi> For <hi>Self-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> is the Foundation of all others, and he that will rule others muſt firſt learn to rule himſelf; his own Paſſions and Affections require his firſt care, and after that then thoſe of other Men. <hi>If a man cannot rule his own houſe, how ſhould he take care of the Church of God,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle?</hi> And I add, If he cannot govern him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:93911:79"/> he can govern neither: For it is the ſureſt way to begin at the bottom, to lay a good Foundation, and ſo build gradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally. The beſt ordered Governments chuſe their Generals out of thoſe that have gone through all the Degrees of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline in the School of War.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <p>§. 11. And yet, after all, it muſt be confeſs'd (and I note it here to prevent an Objection) That Deſert is not always re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded, nor Merit crown'd, in this World. Some precious ſtones muſt lie buried in the Earth. 'Tis not fit Nature ſhould be quite rifled of all her Treaſure at once, and have all her Rarities ſhown together: For if ſhe had no reſerve, ſhe might be bankrupt, and her Treaſures would be ſoon exhauſted. There is not Reward enough perhaps in the World to ſatisfie all Rivals; and the Fountains of Honour are not infinite, but have their Bounds: beſides it is but reaſonable that ſome things ſhould be reſerv'd for the Rewards as well as Puniſhments of the other World, and we may well imagine this to be the deſign of Providence when it ſeems not to regard Vertue or Vice in
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:93911:80"/> this. All that I have hitherto pleaded for, is, That Vertue is uſually rewarded in this Life, and that with Honours; or, at leaſt, Reverence as part of its Portion. That the <hi>Autarchiſt,</hi> (the good Man that can govern himſelf) is uſually thought the fitteſt to govern others; and that ſuch a Man ſhall be eſteem'd and rever'd, even by the moſt diſorderly. But if at any time it falls out otherwiſe, if Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence (for reaſons beſt known to it ſelf, perhaps for our own Good) ſhall ſo far alter the courſe of Nature and diſpoſitions of Mankind, as to ſuffer Deſert not to meet with due Reſpect; be not you (<hi>Doro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus</hi>) yet diſcouraged in your Race of Vertue, for the more is reſerv'd for you when you arrive at the End. Be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent therefore to be a Jewel, though ſometimes you lie neglected in the Duſt; and to ſhine, though none takes notice of you. 'Tis a greater thing to deſerve to be a Prince, than to be one actually; and he is indeed a King that reigns over himſelf and his own Appetites, though he hath none other Subjects. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that Vertue is its own Reward here, though it had neither Riches nor Honours
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:93911:80"/> attending; beſides it muſt be rewarded hereafter. Thoſe internal Bleſſings of Peace and Joy are its own, and, when it hath no other Reward in this World, (which is very ſeldom) God takes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it, and <hi>his Reward is with him, and the greater becauſe deferr'd.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore upon the whole matter, I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, That <hi>Autarchy</hi> is the only way to true Glory here, and Immortality here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <p>§. 12. By this time you muſt confeſs that Godlineſs (and <hi>Autarchy</hi> is nothing elſe, but the Power it exerts over the furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and raging Paſſions) hath uſually the promiſe of this Life, as well as that which is to come. That her outward Advantages are great as well as her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. <hi>Her ways are ways of Pleaſantneſs, and all her paths are Peace. Length of days are in her Right hand, and in her Left Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and Honours.</hi> Theſe are the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges that <hi>Solomon</hi> annexes to a Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Wiſdom, of which <hi>Self-Government</hi> is the greateſt and hardeſt part. I might here further add to its Advantages that of outward Peace with Men, (for Peace of Mind was proved to be her gift in the
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:93911:81"/> laſt Diſcourſe) the quiet I mean, Good Will and Neighbourhood, ſhe would ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in the World; and the Diſſentions ſhe would baniſh out of it: It would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the terreſtrial Paradiſe again, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with its priſtine Innocence, and make that a Tempel of God, which is now become a den of Thieves: It would caſt out the Devil of Hatred and Malice, of Self-Love and Covetouſneſs, of Pride and Revenge (thoſe Fiends that will not ſuffer us to live in Peace) and reſtore Love, Meekneſs, and Humility to bring the Frame of Nature in order again. Thus it would make us all happy if we would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of Happineſs; and we ſhould, while we live here, have ſome Fore-taſtes of the Felicity we are to receive hereafter. Theſe are ſome of the Advantages of <hi>Autarchy:</hi> I might add many other, and make many ingenious and ſurprizing Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations thereupon. But it is time to retire, and try to practiſe mine own ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices: Beſides, I have in ſome meaſure diſcharg'd the Promiſe made in the Firſt of theſe Eſſays, and therefore after a brief review of the whole, I will deſcend to the Concluſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:93911:81"/>
               <p>§. 13. You have heard therefore (my ſtudious <hi>Dorotheus</hi>) in the Firſt Paper the Doctrine of <hi>Autarchy</hi> explain'd, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the ſeveral Rules of Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice. In the Second I have, I hope, ſatisfied, you that its Pleaſures are true, ſubſtantial, and durable; whilſt thoſe of <hi>Senſuality</hi> are deluſive, uncertain, and unſatisfactory: That its <hi>regimen</hi> is not ſo grievous or difficult as the World would perſuade you; but that it is attended with the beſt inward and outward Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. In this Laſt I have endeavoured to ſhew its outward Advantages, as Health, Long Life, Riches and Honours in this World, as well as Eternal Life in the World to come; if it fails in any outward Bleſſing, 'tis but in order to a greater; it naturally leads to 'em, and if it ſometimes miſs let not that be your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement: Food may, by accident<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cauſe Diſeaſes, and that which is the means of Life, cauſe Death. However, it cannot fail of Life with the <hi>Ancient of days,</hi> and the Riches and Honours of a Heavenly Kingdom. This is the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of what I have writ upon this Subject; and my Deſign and great End
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:93911:82"/> in all this, is to excite you to the Practice of thoſe Vertues included under the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Autarchy;</hi> and ſuch are Patience, Meekneſs, Humility, Temperance, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinency, Charity and ſuch like. And to this End, I will commend to you theſe Conſiderations.</p>
               <p>I. It is a Duty not only according to original and incorrupt Nature (in which the lower part is deſign'd to obey the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and join'd to it for its ſervice) but alſo worthy of it. It is the peculiar Character of a good and wiſe man, of him that lives the Life of Angels here, and is deſign'd to live with them here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after: It is the only way to reſtore the defac'd Image of God, recover our loſt Integrity, and the Aethereal Seats from whence we are fallen, which is our buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in this World; for we are ſent hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be exerciſed in Vertue, that we may be fitted for Light and Glory: And he that doth not anſwer this end of his Creation in this Life, ſhall ſink down in the next; he ſhall have cauſe to lament that he had any Being here, and ſhall be ſo much the more miſerable, by how much he might have been happy.</p>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:93911:82"/>
               <p>II. It is an Exerciſe that hath the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality of all the true Pleaſures that God uſually beſtows upon the Sons of Men, in this Vale of Tears; whilſt the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of Sin are falſe, counterfeit, and momentary: Beſides, it is a Preparative for future and greater Joys, when God ſhall lift up our poor dejected Souls out of their terreſtrial Priſons, to the Aethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real Seats and Offices nearer to himſelf. To which add, That it hath (as you have heard prov'd) all the outward Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages we can expect in this ſtate of Darkneſs and Death. For it hath been evidenced, That nothing can tend more to Health and Long Life, Riches, Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, Reſpect; yea, an immortal Name (if any ſuch thing can be obtain'd here, or is worth the purſuit,) than this Great Duty. Thus 'tis an Aggregate of all the poor preſent Joys of theſe lower Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and an earneſt of thoſe of a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; and if any thing can make us happy here, 'tis only this.</p>
               <p>III. It is an Exerciſe that the World, as well as Religion, will in ſome ſenſe exact of us: For though Chriſtianity requires ſtricter Rules of Diſcipline for the Body,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:93911:83"/> by how much its Principles are higher, nobler, and more remov'd from Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reity; yet <hi>Autarchy</hi> is daily (and in ſome reſpects muſt be) uſed in every condition of Life. Every prudent Man muſt uſe it, and ſo hath done from the beginning; and that Man doth not live who denies himſelf nothing. If mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Deſires were all to be ſatisfied, they would be ſoon too clamorous to be endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and would, in a ſhort time, deſtroy themſelves as well as us. We daily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny our ſelves ſome thing, and look upon it to be no burthen, but are content ſo to do. Subjects deny themſelves the Pleaſures of Regality, and Princes wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly relinquiſh the Liberty and Receſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Subjects. The poor are content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o fare hard, and be without the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieties of the Rich Man's Table, and the Rich Man is forc'd to want the Appetite and Freedom of the Poor. We look upon it to be our Fate to be without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things, upon prudential and ſecular Accounts. The World will enjoin <hi>Self-Government,</hi> without the cenſure of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, and why may not Religion? Be but then as wife for your Soul as you are
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:93911:83"/> for your Body or Eſtate, and you need no more. The other World may ſure engage you as far as this.</p>
               <p>IV. And Laſtly (that I may come nearer your ſelf, and your preſent Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances), It is an Exerciſe that can only ſuit with your Education under the beſt Diſcipline and the moſt learned place under Heaven<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It is the true End of all your Studies at School and in the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity. It is the Aim of thoſe excellent Men that have the educating of Youth, the cultivating of Natures, and the dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Souls in every Seminary of Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. It is the End of your Friends Cares and Fears for you; of the Sciences that you have ſtudied, and the Degrees you have taken: and particularly of the higheſt and moſt uſeful Science, called Moral Philoſophy. As to Phyſicks, there be many things in Nature inexpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable, and ſo are like to remain till this Dream of Life is over: And other things are explicated ſeveral ways, by ſeveral Men, endleſly confuting each other (ſo that ſome have concluded to ſit down with a Reſolution to profeſs to know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing;) but Morality, or the Doctrine
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:93911:84"/> of conforming our Manners to the Rules of Vertue, is plain, eaſie, and certain. And while other Sciences may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted to vain and ſinful Ends and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, the Morality of the Schools is the Hand-maid to that of Divinity, and leads to that we learn of Chriſt. It has an inherent holineſs in it, and is not ſubject to Perverſions; and the Moraliſt ſhall he ſtill accounted (as he was once by the <hi>Oracle</hi>) the wiſeſt and the beſt Man: For this Learning (eſpecially that part that teaches you to govern your ſelf) <hi>è coelo deſcendit,</hi> deſcended from above, and directs us thither.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <p>§. 14. Nor are you to deferr the Duty of <hi>Autarchy,</hi> or the governing your ſelf till Old Age or a fiter Seaſon in your Judgment, but ſet your ſelf to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Practice of it. And againſt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laying of this or any other Duty, I muſt lay before you theſe Five Conſiderations.</p>
               <p>1. Our Life is uncertain, neither have we here a continuing City, but muſt, we know not how ſoon, be turn'd out into the vaſt Abyſs of Eternity to ſeek one. In all the Periods of our Time, Death attends us as well as in Old Age, and our
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:93911:84"/> laſt Day is both certain and uncertain to us: For God, when he ſent us hither, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotted us our times, long or ſhort, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Will and our Neceſſities, and in proportion to our Wants and his Goodneſs. And he hath wiſely hid the Bounds and Limits of theſe our times in Darkneſs and unknown Futurity; ſo that we cannot find them out till we have paſſed them: And this the rather, that no Man might preſume upon his remaining Sand, deferr Repentance, or depend upon any but God for Life. That we might always expect, what (for ought we know) may befal us at any time, and make every Day our laſt, becauſe it may prove ſo.</p>
               <p>2. Though we cannot find out the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſions of our Lives, which are hid with God, and <hi>beyond which we cannot paſs,</hi> as <hi>Job</hi> tells us, <hi>Job</hi> 14. 5. Yet, I ſuppoſe, it lies in our own power to ſhorten them, and ſo curtail that Bleſſing that Heaven deſign'd for us: For I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that thoſe Terms and Limits are aſſign'd Conditionally, and upon ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of our uſing the beſt Means and right Management of our ſelves. And,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:93911:85"/> conſequently, in theſe licentious Times, few Men reach thoſe Bounds ſet by God and Nature: And though, it may be, we cannot enlarge thoſe Terms ſet for us (which I am apt to believe, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with <hi>Job</hi>'s Words afore-mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;) yet it doth not follow but we may ſhorten them. Thus Exceſſes carry us off betimes; and Debauchery diſpatches us in a few Years: the Sword hath ſlain its thouſands; but Senſuality its ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands. It is beyond the power of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick to reſtore what we conſume and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy; and we are moſt of us at all times, and all of us at ſome time or other (God forgive us) a kind of <hi>felo de ſe</hi>'s, or Self-Murtherers. <hi>Autarchy</hi> muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be begun betimes, becauſe it can then only bring us to our Journey's end, and ſave us from the imputation of contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to our own Death.</p>
               <p>3. 'Tis a fooliſh and dangerous thing to put off that which we muſt, not only begin, but perfectly exerciſe at one time or other, or elſe be miſerable. It is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to all the Methods of Wiſdom and Prudence in the world, to deferr a thing of that infinite concern to us, as
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:93911:85"/> Salvation, or the Means requiſite there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. Procraſtination may poſſibly make us miſerable in a moment, but it can never do us the leaſt good.</p>
               <p>4. God, with whom are the Meaſures of Life, and the fatal Bounds which we may not paſs, may juſtly reſent our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay, and offer us his Grace no more. He that ſlights his great Concerns in this World, when he hath Opportunity, may juſtly have that Opportuity taken away from him; and who knows but God may enlarge or abbreviate our Lives, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as we uſe or abuſe his Tenders of Grace. However, the Door may be ſhut, and the day of Salvation may end before that of Nature. The Scripture tells us, <hi>To him that hath ſhall be given, and he ſhall have abundance; but from him that hath not, ſhall be taken away that which he ſeemeth to have.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>5. And Laſtly, Procraſtinators ſeldom begin, much leſs finiſh any Religious Work. And there is this reaſon to be given for it, The ſame Cauſe which makes you deferr a thing to day, will to morrow, and ſo forward. And if Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, Idleneſs, or Want of Inclination
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:93911:86"/> be that cauſe to day, it will be more to morrow, and ſo forward. The longer the work of <hi>Self-Conqueſt</hi> is deferr'd, the harder it will grow, till it becomes inſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perable, and the more will be your A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion to it. The Fleſh, which at firſt is tractable and tender, will (if left to its own Management) become ſtubborn and hard to be bowed. And therefore it hath been obſerved, That Procraſtinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not only a Sign but a Cauſe of final Impenitency. Remember, therefore, the Sentence with which a late pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Author concludes his Book, out of the Mouth of the wiſe <hi>Siracides. Make no tarrying to turn to the Lord, and put it not off from day to day.</hi> Eccluſ. 5. 7.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <p>§. 15. The Concluſion of all ſhall be hortative, and (that it may have the more Effect) in the words of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> quoted and approv'd of by St. <hi>Peter;</hi> and ſo declaring the Senſe of the Old and New Law about the Duty of <hi>Autarchy,</hi> and its preſent Reward. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. 12, &amp;c. and 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 10, &amp;c. <hi>What Man is he that deſireth Life, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth many days, that he may ſee good? Keep thy Tongue from evil, and thy Lips
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:93911:86"/> from ſpeaking guile. Depart from evil and do good, ſeek peace and enſue it. For the Eyes of the Lord are upon the righteous, and his Ears are open to their prayers; but the face of the Lord is againſt them that do evil, to cut off the remembrance of them from the earth.</hi> In which words the great Duty is <hi>Autarchy,</hi> which conſiſts (1.) in the <hi>Government of the Tongue,</hi> from Raillery and Falſhood; (2.) <hi>of the Actions,</hi> in declining every evil Act, and doing that which is good; (3.) <hi>of the Mind,</hi> that it be free from the unruly Paſſions, peaceable in it ſelf, and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able with all men. Thus for the Duty; then for the Reward, It in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſes the Duty on all ſides, that one may not be ſeen without the other. It promiſes (1.) Temporal Bleſſings, as moſt agreeable and taking with fleſh and blood, <hi>viz.</hi> Long Life, Many Days, and Enjoyment of Good in them: And then adds. (2.) Spiritual Bleſſings, and theſe follow the Duty; <hi>God's Eyes,</hi> i. e. his gracious Aſpect or Providence, <hi>watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es over the righteous, and his Ears are open to their Prayers;</hi> whereas, on the other ſide, <hi>he ſets himſelf in oppoſition to them
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:93911:87"/> that do evil, his Face</hi> or Countenance <hi>is againſt the Senſualiſt, not only to cut him off from the earth; but the very Memory of him, his place and name, ſo that they ſhall no where be found.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You ſee then (<hi>Dorotheus</hi>) both your Duty and Reward. And what now can be expected from you, upon the whole matter, but that you ſhould act like your ſelf, as a Man of Reaſon and Underſtanding; and, having the Candle of the Lord for your Guide, that you follow its Light in all things. Do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing therefore, unworthy of your Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Learning; and entertain no Thought that may be a ſhame to either. Bring every intended Action to the Teſt, and examine it before the upper Court of Judicature. Avoid Self-condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as the greateſt evil; and ſcorn to do that in private, which you dare not own in publick. Eſchew not only every ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but every unworthy Action; and abſtain not only from Evil, but from the very appearance of it. Deſire no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what is neceſſary and proper for you; and ſuſpect every Licentious Act, though there appears no preſent Sin
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:93911:87"/> in it. Uſe your Body to ſome Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, and accuſtom it to Diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments now and then, that it may the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier bear the non-enjoyment of things prohibited. Keep it and its Appetites at a diſtance and under the rod; and if it rebels, exerciſe it with Faſting and Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence. In a word, Be abſolute in your ſelf, and tolerate no Reſiſtance there.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <p>§. 16. Thus taught <hi>Socrates</hi> that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Image of Wiſdom, and <hi>Plato</hi> the God-like, and the reſt of the wiſe and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient Sons of Nature, enlightened only by the glimmering Candle-light of its Laws. Nay, thus taught and liv'd the Holy Jeſus, and ſpent his time here in Faſting, Prayer, and other ſpiritual Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes, not out of any neceſſity in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of himſelf, but that he might give us an Example: He willingly choſe Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings and Poverty rather than Empire, and preferr'd Sorrow to Mirth, as more proper for a Vale of Tears. Thus liv'd and taught his holy Apoſtles and firſt Followers, denying themſelves, chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their Bodies, and keeping them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and that not only for Cure, but for
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:93911:88"/> Prevention. And thus liv'd and taught the Primitive Saints for ſome hundreds of Years; till Iniquity began to abound and the divine Love to wax cold: Many of whom (that they might be more than Conquerours, ſhew the Power they had over themſelves, and avoid Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) choſe to prevent Death, and die whilſt they lived; leave the World, I mean, and all its Vanities and Follies, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon Delights, renounce all humane Converſation, deny themſelves even in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Entertainments, and ſhut them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves up from the power of Vain-glory and all Society. And this was the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal of a Monaſtick Life.</p>
               <p>I know very well that there is no Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of going thus far, and that even this ſort of Deſertion of the World hath degenerated into Hypocriſie. That the blackeſt Crimes have been acted in the dark, and the greateſt Licentiouſneſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Monk's Cowl and Hood. I know likewiſe that no Man is neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to take upon him the Vow of Coeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacy, or to forſake the World in that Senſe. Our Lot is eaſier than theirs, who were forced to fly to the Mountains,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:93911:88"/> and ſpend their times in Solitudes. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is (God be thanked) both com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded and rewarded; and <hi>Autarchy</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir'd by all, though us'd by few. But this is that I have and muſt maintain, That we muſt <hi>keep our ſelves unſpotted from the World, and the ſinful Luſts of the Fleſh.</hi> And, in order thereunto, That we muſt learn the Art of <hi>Self-Conqueſt,</hi> by the moſt convenient and ſuitable Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods; and that we ought to be prepar'd to ſuffer, though we have no preſent E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy or outward War. That Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is a ſpiritual Warfare; and that we have the Devil, and our own Luſts to combate and conquer. And, finally, That thoſe good and wiſe Men, which like ſo many Stars illuminate theſe dark Regions of Sin and Ignorance, ought to be <hi>Autarchiſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Shine then (my <hi>Dorotheus</hi>) amongſt theſe few: for thus only ſhall you enſure inward Quiet and Peace amongſt the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainties of an unconſtant World; you will experiment true external Pleaſures, beſides the Comforts of a pure Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which nothing can take from you; you will find inward Pleaſure and Peace,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:93911:89"/> if not that which outward, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably Long Life, Health, Credit, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, and many good days. The ſtrait Gate will grow wider, and the narrow Path broader, and <hi>Autarchy</hi> will at laſt prove your Reward as well as Duty: You will begin here to live the Spiritual Life, the Life of Angels and beatified Souls; which, as you grow older, will become more and more delightful; till at laſt you meet Death diſarm'd of all its Terrours, lovely and charming, becauſe it will conduct your willing Soul to the Regions of Bliſs, and to the Company of Angels. Which is the daily Prayer of your Friend, and the Deſign of theſe Papers.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:93911:89"/>
            <head>A <hi>Catalogue</hi> of <hi>Books</hi> Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for <hi>Dorman Newman.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Way to Health, Long-Life and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs: or, A Diſcourſe of <hi>Temperance,</hi> and the particular nature of all things requiſite for the Life of Man: as all ſorts of <hi>Meats, Drinks, Age, Exerciſe,</hi> &amp;c. with ſpecial Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections how to uſe each of them to the beſt advantage of the Body and Mind. Shewing, from the true ground of Nature, whence moſt Diſeaſes proceed, and how to prevent them. To which is added a Treatiſe of the moſt ſort of <hi>Engliſh Herbs,</hi> with ſeveral other remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and moſt uſeful Obſervations, <hi>Very neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for all Families.</hi> The whole Treatiſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playing the moſt hidden Secrets of Philoſophy, and made eaſie and familiar to the meaneſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities, by various Examples and Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. <hi>By T. Tryon.</hi> The Second Edition, with Amendments. Alſo the other Works of the Authour.</p>
            <p>A Brief Expoſition of the <hi>Church-Catechiſm,</hi> with Proofs from Scripture. By Dr. <hi>Williams.</hi> The Third Edition.</p>
            <p>The Penitent Lady: or, Reflections on the Mercy of God. Written by the Fam'd Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>La Valliere,</hi> ſince her retirement from the <hi>French</hi> Court to a Nunnery. Tranſlated from the French, by <hi>L. A.</hi> M. A. The Second Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:93911:90"/>
            <p>Contemplations on the ſtate of Man in this Life, and in that which is to come. By Bp. <hi>Taylor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Golden Chain, to link the Penitent Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner unto God. Whereunto is added a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the Immortality of the Soul.</p>
            <p>A Moral Diſcourſe of the Power of Intereſt. By <hi>David Abercromby,</hi> M. D. and Fellow of the College of Phyſicians at <hi>Amſterdam.</hi> The Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Edition.</p>
            <p>Letters of advice from two Reverend Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, to a young Gentleman, about <hi>A weighty Caſe of Conſcience.</hi> And by him recommended to the ſerious Peruſal of all thoſe that may fall into the ſame Condition. <hi>Fly youthful Luſts.</hi> 2 Tim. 2. 22.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Willet</hi>'s <hi>Synopſis Papiſmi:</hi> or, a general View of Popery. Wherein the whole <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity,</hi> maintained by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> is Confuted by <hi>Scripture, Fathers, Councils, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Conſtitutions, Pontifical Decrees, Their own Writers, Our Martyrs,</hi> and <hi>The Conſent of all Chriſtian Churches in the World.</hi> Divided into Five Books or Centuries, containing ſo many Hundreds of <hi>Popiſh Hereſies</hi> and <hi>Errours.</hi> To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Life and Death of the Learned Authour. This Book hath been Five times Printed, and contains near 400 ſheets in large Folio; there being a ſmall number left, they are propoſed to be ſold at <hi>7s. 6d.</hi> in Sheets, or <hi>10s.</hi> bound.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shelton</hi>'s Art of <hi>Short-Writing,</hi> both ſorts, <hi>Tachygraphia</hi> and <hi>Zeiglographia.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
